<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629-xhtml.ent">

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="no"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc authorship="yes"?>
<?rfc tocappendix="yes"?>
<rfc  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" category="info" ipr='trust200902' tocInclude="true"  obsoletes="" updates="" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en" version="3" docName="draft-ietf-raw-technologies-08" >

<front>
   <title abbrev='RAW Technologies'>Reliable and Available Wireless Technologies</title>
   <author initials='P' surname='Thubert' fullname='Pascal Thubert' role='editor'>
      <organization abbrev='Cisco Systems'>Cisco Systems, Inc</organization>
      <address>
          <postal>
            <street>Emerald Square, Batiment C</street>
            <street>rue Evariste Galois </street>
            <city>BIOT - Sophia Antipolis</city>
            <code>06410</code>
          <country>France</country>
         </postal>
         <phone>+33 497 23 26 34</phone>
         <email>pthubert@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
   </author>
   <author initials='D' surname='Cavalcanti' fullname='Dave Cavalcanti'>
      <organization abbrev='Intel'>Intel Corporation</organization>
      <address>
         <postal>
            <street>2111 NE 25th Ave </street>
            <city> Hillsboro, OR</city>
            <code>97124</code>
            <country>USA</country>
         </postal>
         <phone>503 712 5566</phone>
         <email>dave.cavalcanti@intel.com</email>
      </address>
   </author>
   <author initials='X' surname='Vilajosana' fullname='Xavier Vilajosana'>
      <organization>Universitat Oberta de Catalunya</organization>
      <address>
         <postal>
            <street>156 Rambla Poblenou</street>
            <city>Barcelona</city>
            <region>Catalonia</region>
            <code>08018</code>
            <country>Spain</country>
         </postal>
         <email>xvilajosana@uoc.edu</email></address>
    </author>

   <author initials='C' surname='Schmitt' fullname='Corinna Schmitt'>
      <organization>Research Institute CODE, UniBw M</organization>
      <address>
         <postal>
            <street>Werner-Heisenberg-Weg 39</street>
            <city>Neubiberg</city>
            <code>85577</code>
            <country>Germany</country>
         </postal>
         <email>corinna.schmitt@unibw.de</email></address>
    </author>
       <author initials='J' surname='Farkas' fullname='Janos Farkas'>
      <organization abbrev='Ericsson'>Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
         <postal>
            <street>Magyar tudosok korutja 11</street>
            <city> Budapest</city>
            <code>1117</code>
            <country>Hungary</country>
         </postal>
         <email>janos.farkas@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
   </author>


   <date/>
   <area>Internet Area</area>
   <workgroup>RAW</workgroup>
   <keyword>Draft</keyword>
   <abstract>
      <t>   This document presents a series of recent technologies that are
      capable of time synchronization and scheduling of transmission, making
      them suitable to carry time-sensitive flows with high reliability and
      availability.
      </t>
   </abstract>
</front>

<middle>
   <section><name>Introduction</name>
   <t>
   When used in math or philosophy, the term "deterministic" generally refers to
   a perfection where all aspects are understood and predictable. A perfectly
   deterministic network would ensure that every packet reaches its destination
   following a predetermined path along a predefined schedule to be delivered at
   the exact due time. In a real and imperfect world, a deterministic network
   must be highly predictable, which is a combination of reliability and
   availability.

   </t>
   <ul>
   <li>
   On the one hand the network must be reliable, meaning that it
   will perform as expected for all but very few packets and in particular
   that it will deliver the packets at the destination within a pre-defined
   time interval.
    </li><li>
   On the other hand, the network must be available, meaning that it has to be
   resilient to any single outage, independently of the cause of the failure,
   be it software, hardware, or external, e.g., a physical event impacting
   the transmission channel.
   </li>
   </ul>
   <t>
   Deterministic Networking (DetNet) <xref target="RFC8557"/> provides a capability to carry specified
   unicast or multicast data flows for real-time applications with extremely low data loss rates and bounded latency within a network
   domain.  Techniques used include 1) reserving data-plane resources
   for individual (or aggregated) DetNet flows in some or all of the
   intermediate nodes along the path of the flow, 2) providing explicit
   routes for DetNet flows that do not immediately change with the
   network topology, and 3) distributing data from DetNet flow packets
   over time and/or space to ensure delivery of each packet's data in
   spite of the loss of a path.  DetNet operates at the IP layer and typically
   delivers service over wired lower-layer technologies such as Time-Sensitive
   Networking (TSN) as defined by IEEE 802.1 and IEEE 802.3.
   </t>
   <t>
   Making wireless reliable and available is even more challenging than it is
   with wires, due to the numerous causes of radio transmission losses that add up
   to the congestion losses and the delays caused by overbooked shared resources.
   The Reliable and Available Wireless (RAW) Architecture <xref target='I-D.ietf-raw-architecture'/> extends the DetNet Architecture <xref target="RFC8655"/>  and other standard IETF concepts and mechanisms to adapt to the specific challenges of the wireless medium, in particular intermittently lossy connectivity, by extending and optimizing the use of diversity and multipathing.
  </t>
   <t>
   RAW, like DetNet, needs and leverages lower-layer capabilities such as time synchronization and traffic shapers. To balance the adverse effects of the radio transmission losses, RAW leverages additional capabilities, some of which maybe more specific to wireless. RAW's Packet (hybrid) ARQ, Replication, Elimination and Ordering (PAREO) can be seen as a superset Of DetNet's PREOF,
   adding techniques such as per-hop retransmissions (aka Automatic Repeat request or ARQ), variating the modulation and coding scheme (MCS), short range broadcast, Multiple User - Multiple Input Multiple Output (MU-MIMO), constructive interference, and overhearing whereby multiple receivers are scheduled to receive the same transmission, which saves both energy on the sender and spectrum. PAREO techniques are offered by the lower layer and may be controlled by RAW separately or in combination.
   </t>
  <t>
   RAW defines a network-layer control loop that optimizes the use of links with constrained spectrum and energy while maintaining the expected connectivity properties, typically reliability and latency. The control loop involves Operations, Administration and Maintenance (OAM), a Path computation Element (PCE), A runtime distributed Path Selection Engine (PSE) and the PAREO functions.
   </t>
   <t>
   This document browses the short and middle range radio technologies that are suitable to provide a DetNet/RAW service over,
   presents the characteristics that RAW may leverage, and explores the applicability of the technologies to carry deterministic flows. The studied technologies are Wi-Fi 6/7, TimeSlotted Channel Hopping (TSCH), 3GPP 5G, and L-band Digital Aeronautical Communications System (LDACS).
   </t>
   </section><!-- title="Introduction"-->

   <section><name>Terminology</name>
   <t>
   This document uses the terminology and acronyms defined in section 2 of <xref target="RFC8655"/> and section 2 of <xref target='I-D.ietf-raw-architecture'/>.
   </t>
   </section><!-- Terminology -->



   <section anchor='detpak'><name>Towards Reliable and Available Networks</name>


   <section anchor='schre'><name>Scheduling for Reliability</name>


   <t>
   A packet network is reliable for critical (e.g., time-sensitive) packets
   when the undesirable statistical effects that affect the transmission of
   those packets, e.g., delay or loss, are eliminated.
   </t>
   <t>
   The reliability of a Deterministic Network <xref target='RFC8655'/>
   often relies on precisely applying a tight schedule that controls the use
   of time-shared resources such as CPUs and buffers, and maintains at all
   time the amount of the critical packets within the physical capabilities of
   the hardware and that of the transmission medium.
   The schedule can also be used to shape the flows by controlling the time of transmission of the packets that compose the flow at every hop.
   </t>
   <t>
   To achieve this, there must be a shared sense of time throughout the network.
   The sense of time is usually provided by the lower layer and is not in
   scope for RAW. As an example, the Precision Time Protocol, standardized as
   IEEE 1588 and IEC 61588, has mapping through profiles to Ethernet, industrial and SmartGrid protocols, and Wi-Fi with IEEE Std 802.1AS.
   </t>
   </section><!-- Towards Reliable and Available Networks -->
   <section anchor='divav'><name>Diversity for Availability</name>
   <t>
   Equipment failure, such as a switch or an access point rebooting, a broken
   wire or radio adapter, or a fixed obstacle to the transmission, can
   be the cause of multiple packets lost in a row before the
   flows are rerouted or the system may recover.
   </t>
   <t>
   This is not acceptable for critical applications such as related to safety.
   A typical process control loop will tolerate an occasional packet loss, but
   a loss of several packets in a row will cause an emergency stop. In an amusement park,
   a continuous loss of packet for a few 100ms may trigger an automatic
   interruption of the ride and cause the evacuation and the reboot of the game.
   </t>
   <t>
   Network Availability is obtained by making the transmission resilient against
   hardware failures and radio transmission losses due to uncontrolled events
   such as co-channel interferers, multipath fading or moving obstacles. The
   best results are typically achieved by pseudo-randomly cumulating all forms
   of diversity, in the spatial domain with replication and elimination, in the
   time domain with ARQ and diverse scheduled transmissions, and in the
   frequency domain with frequency hopping or channel hopping between frames.

   </t>
   </section><!-- Diversity for Availability -->



   <section anchor='wessbenef'><name>Benefits of Scheduling</name>

   <t>
   Scheduling redundant transmissions of the critical packets on diverse paths
   improves the resiliency against breakages and statistical transmission
   loss, such as due to cosmic particles on wires, and interferences on
   wireless.
   </t>
   <t>
   When required, the worst case time of delivery can be guaranteed as part of
   the end-to-end schedule, and the sense of time that must be shared
   throughout the network can be exposed to and leveraged by other applications.
   </t>
   <t>
   In addition, scheduling provides specific value over the wireless medium:
   </t>
   <ul>
   <li>
   Scheduling allows a time-sharing operation, where every transmission is assigned its own time/frequency resource. Sender and receiver are synchronized and scheduled to talk on a given frequency resource at a given time and for a given duration. This way, scheduling can avoid collisions between scheduled transmissions and enable a high ratio of critical traffic
   compared to QoS-based priority.
   </li>
   <li>
   Scheduling can be used as a technoque for both time and frequency diversity (e.g., between retries), allowing the next transmission to happen on a different frequency as programmed in both sender and receiver.
   This is useful to defeat co-channel interference from un-controlled
   transmitters as well as multipath fading.
   </li>
   <li>
   Transmissions can be also scheduled on multiple channels in parallel,
   which enables to use the full available spectrum while avoiding the
   hidden terminal problem, e.g., when the next packet in a same flow interferes
   on a same channel with the previous one that progressed a few hops farther.
   </li>
   <li>
   On the other hand, scheduling optimizes the bandwidth usage: compared to
   classical Collision Avoidance techniques, there is no blank time related to
   inter-frame space (IFS) and exponential back-off in scheduled operations.
   A minimal Clear Channel Assessment may be needed to comply with the local
   regulations such as ETSI 300-328, but that will not detect a collision when
   the senders are synchronized.
   </li>
   <li>
   Finally, scheduling plays a critical role to save energy. In IoT, energy is
   the foremost concern, and synchronizing sender and listener enables to
   always maintain them in deep sleep when there is no scheduled
   transmission. This avoids idle listening and long preambles and enables long
   sleep periods between traffic and resynchronization, allowing
   battery-operated nodes to operate in a mesh topology for multiple years.
   </li>
   </ul>
   </section><!-- Benefits of Scheduling on Wireless -->


   </section><!-- Towards Reliable and Available Networks -->

   <section><name>IEEE 802.11</name>
        <section><name>Provenance and Documents</name>

   <t>
   With an active portfolio of nearly 1,300 standards and projects under development, IEEE is a leading developer of industry standards in a broad range of technologies that drive the functionality, capabilities, and interoperability of products and services, transforming how people live, work, and communicate.
   </t>

   <t>
   The IEEE 802 LAN/MAN Standards Committee (SC) develops and maintains networking standards and recommended practices for local, metropolitan, and other area networks, using an open and accredited process, and advocates them on a global basis. The most widely used standards are for Ethernet, Bridging and Virtual Bridged LANs Wireless LAN, Wireless PAN, Wireless MAN, Wireless Coexistence, Media Independent Handover Services, and Wireless RAN. An individual Working Group provides the focus for each area. Standards produced by the IEEE 802 SC are freely available from the IEEE GET Program after they have been published in PDF for six months.
   </t>
        <t>
        	The IEEE 802.11 Wireless LAN (WLAN) standards define the underlying MAC and PHY layers for the Wi-Fi technology. Wi-Fi/802.11 is one of the most successful wireless technologies, supporting many application domains. While previous 802.11 generations, such as 802.11n and 802.11ac, have focused mainly on improving peak throughput, more recent generations are also considering other performance vectors, such as efficiency enhancements for dense environments in 802.11ax, throughput, latency, and reliability enhancements in P802.11be.
        	</t>
        <t>
        	IEEE Std 802.11-2012 introduced support for TSN time synchronization based on IEEE 802.1AS over 802.11 Timing Measurement protocol. IEEE Std 802.11-2016 extended the 802.1AS operation over 802.11 Fine Timing Measurement (FTM), as well as the Stream Reservation Protocol (IEEE 802.1Qat). 802.11 WLANs can also be part of a 802.1Q bridged networks with enhancements enabled by the 802.11ak amendment now retrofitted in IEEE Std 802.11-2020. Traffic classification based on 802.1Q VLAN tags is also supported in 802.11. Other 802.1 TSN capabilities such as 802.1Qbv and 802.1CB, which are media agnostic, can already operate over 802.11. The IEEE Std 802.11ax-2021 adds new scheduling capabilities that can enhance the timeliness performance in the 802.11 MAC and achieve lower bounded latency. The IEEE 802.11be is undergoing efforts to enhance the support for 802.1 TSN capabilities especially related to worst-case latency, reliability and availability.

	</t>
    <t>
		The IEEE 802.11 working group has been working in collaboration with the IEEE 802.1 working group for several years extending some 802.1 features over 802.11. As with any wireless media, 802.11 imposes new constraints and restrictions to TSN-grade QoS, and tradeoffs between latency and reliability guarantees must be considered as well as managed deployment requirements. An overview of 802.1 TSN capabilities and challenges for their extensions to 802.11 are discussed in <xref target='Cavalcanti_2019'/>.
     		</t>
     		<t>
            Wi-Fi Alliance (WFA) is the worldwide network of companies that drives global Wi-Fi adoption and evolution through thought leadership, spectrum advocacy, and industry-wide collaboration. The WFA work helps ensure that Wi-Fi devices and networks provide users the interoperability, security, and reliability they have come to expect.
        	</t>
        	<t>
	    Avnu Alliance is also a global industry forum developing interoperability testing for TSN capable devices across multiple media including Ethernet, Wi-Fi, and 5G.
		</t>
		<t>
     		The following <xref target='IEEE80211'/> specifications/certifications are relevant in the context of reliable and available wireless services and support for time-sensitive networking capabilities:
     		</t><dl  spacing='normal'>
            <dt>Time Synchronization:</dt><dd> IEEE802.11-2016 with IEEE802.1AS; WFA TimeSync Certification.</dd>
            <dt>Congestion Control:</dt><dd> IEEE Std 802.11-2016 Admission Control; WFA Admission Control.</dd>
            <dt>Security:</dt><dd> WFA Wi-Fi Protected Access, WPA2 and WPA3.</dd>
            <dt>Interoperating with IEEE802.1Q bridges:</dt><dd> IEEE Std 802.11-2020 incorporating 802.11ak.</dd>
            <dt>Stream Reservation Protocol (part of <xref target='IEEE8021Qat'/>):</dt><dd> AIEEE802.11-2016</dd>
            <dt>Scheduled channel access:</dt><dd> IEEE802.11ad Enhancements for very high throughput in the 60 GHz band <xref target='IEEE80211ad'/>.</dd>
            <dt>802.11 Real-Time Applications:</dt><dd> Topic Interest Group (TIG) ReportDoc <xref target='IEEE_doc_11-18-2009-06'/>.</dd>
          </dl><t>
         </t>

        <t>
        In addition, major amendments being developed by the IEEE802.11 Working Group include capabilities that can be used as the basis for providing more reliable and predictable wireless connectivity and support time-sensitive applications:
        </t><dl  spacing='normal'>
        	<dt>IEEE 802.11ax  D4.0: Enhancements for High Efficiency (HE).</dt><dd><xref target='IEEE80211ax'/></dd>
        	<dt>IEEE 802.11be Extreme High Throughput (EHT).</dt><dd><xref target='IEEE80211be'/></dd>
        	<dt>IEE 802.11ay Enhanced throughput for operation in license-exempt bands above 45 GHz.</dt><dd> <xref target='IEEE80211ay'/></dd>
        	</dl><t>
        </t>
     		<t>
     		The main 802.11ax, 802.11be, 802.11ad, and 802.11ay capabilities and their relevance to RAW are discussed in the remainder of this section.
            </t>
        </section> <!-- Provenance and Documents-->
        <section anchor="HE"><name>802.11ax High Efficiency (HE)</name>
        	<section><name>General Characteristics</name>
        		<t>
        			The next generation Wi-Fi (Wi-Fi 6) is based on the IEEE802.11ax amendment <xref target='IEEE80211ax'/>, which includes new capabilities to increase efficiency, control and reduce latency. Some of the new features include higher order 1024-QAM modulation, support for uplink  multiple user (MU) multiple input multiple output (MIMO), orthogonal frequency-division multiple access (OFDMA), trigger-based access and Target Wake time (TWT) for enhanced power savings. The OFDMA mode and trigger-based access enable the AP, after reserving the channel using the clear channel assessment procedure for a given duration, to schedule multi-user transmissions, which is a key capability required to increase latency predictability and reliability for time-sensitive flows. 802.11ax can operate in up to 160 MHz channels and it includes support for operation in the new 6 GHz band, which is expected to be open to unlicensed use by the FCC and other regulatory agencies worldwide.
        			</t>
        		<section><name>Multi-User OFDMA and Trigger-based Scheduled Access</name>
        			<t>
        				802.11ax introduced a new OFDMA mode in which multiple users can be scheduled across the frequency domain. In this mode, the Access Point (AP) can initiate multi-user (MU) Uplink (UL) transmissions in the same PHY Protocol Data Unit (PPDU) by sending a trigger frame. This centralized scheduling capability gives the AP much more control of the channel in its Basic Service Set (BSS) and it can remove contention between associated stations for uplink transmissions, therefore reducing the randomness caused by CSMA-based access between stations within the same BSS. The AP can also transmit simultaneously to multiple users in the downlink direction by using a Downlink (DL) MU OFDMA PPDU. In order to initiate a contention free Transmission Opportunity (TXOP) using the OFDMA mode, the AP still follows the typical listen before talk procedure to acquire the medium, which ensures interoperability and compliance with unlicensed band access rules. However, 802.11ax also includes a multi-user Enhanced Distributed Channel Access (MU-EDCA) capability, which allows the AP to get higher channel access priority than other devices in its BSS.
        			</t>
        		</section> <!--Multi-User OFDMA and Trigger-based Scheduled Access -->


                  		<section><name>Traffic Isolation via OFDMA Resource Management and Resource Unit Allocation</name>
<t>

 802.11ax relies on the notion of OFDMA Resource Unit (RU) to allocate
 frequency chunks to different STAs over time. RUs provide a way to allow
 for multiple stations to transmit simultaneously, starting and ending at
 the same time. The way this is achieved is via padding, where extra bits
 are transmitted with the same power level. The current RU allocation
 algorithms provide a way to achieve traffic isolation per station which
 while per se does not support time-aware scheduling, is a key aspect to
 assist reliability, as it provides traffic isolation in a shared medium.
 IEEE 802.11be (see <xref target="EHT"/>) is currently considering further and more flexible approaches concerning RU allocation.

</t>
                  		</section><!-- Traffic Isolation via OFDMA Resource Management and Resource Unit -->
        		<section><name>Improved PHY Robustness</name>
        			<t>
        				The 802.11ax PHY can operate with 0.8, 1.6 or 3.2 microsecond guard interval (GI). The larger GI options provide better protection against multipath, which is expected to be a challenge in industrial environments. The possibility to operate with smaller resource units (e.g. 2 MHz) enabled by OFDMA also helps reduce noise power and improve SNR, leading to better packet error rate (PER) performance.
        			</t>
        			<t>
        				802.11ax supports beamforming as in 802.11ac, but introduces UL MU MIMO, which helps improve reliability. The UL MU MIMO capability is also enabled by the trigger based access operation in 802.11ax.
        				</t>
        		</section> <!-- Improved PHY Robustness -->
        		<section><name>Support for 6GHz band</name>
        				<t>
        					The 802.11ax specification <xref target='IEEE80211ax'/> includes support for operation in the new 6 GHz band. Given the amount of new spectrum available as well as the fact that no legacy 802.11 device (prior 802.11ax) will be able to operate in this new band, 802.11ax operation in this new band can be even more efficient.
        					</t>
        		</section> <!-- Support for 6GHz band -->
        	</section> <!-- General Characteristics-->

        <section><name>Applicability to deterministic flows</name>
        	<t>
        		TSN capabilities, as defined by the IEEE 802.1 TSN standards, provide the underlying mechanism for supporting deterministic flows in a Local Area Network (LAN). The 802.11 working group has incorporated support for absolute time synchronization to extend the TSN 802.1AS protocol so that time-sensitive flow can experience precise time synchronization when operating over 802.11 links. As IEEE 802.11 and IEEE 802.1 TSN are both based on the IEEE 802 architecture, 802.11 devices can directly implement some TSN capabilities without the need for a gateway/translation protocol. Basic features required for operation in a 802.1Q LAN are already enabled for 802.11. Some TSN capabilities, such as 802.1Qbv, can already operate over the existing 802.11 MAC SAP <xref target='Sudhakaran2021'/>. Implementation and experimental results of TSN capabilities (802.1AS, 802.1Qbv, and 802.1CB) extended over standard Ethernet and Wi-Fi devices have also been described in <xref target='Fang_2021'/>. Nevertheless, the IEEE 802.11 MAC/PHY could be extended to improve the operation of IEEE 802.1 TSN features and achieve better performance metrics <xref target='Cavalcanti1287'/>.
                </t><t>
                TSN capabilities supported over 802.11 (which also extends to 802.11ax), include:
        		</t>
                <ol type='%d.'>
        		<li> 802.1AS based Time Synchronization (other time synchronization techniques may also be used) </li>
        		<li> Interoperating with IEEE802.1Q bridges</li>
        		<li> Time-sensitive Traffic Stream Classification</li>
        		</ol>
        	<t>
        			The existing 802.11 TSN capabilities listed above, and the 802.11ax OFDMA and AP-controlled access within a BSS provide a new set of tools to better serve time-sensitive flows. However, it is important to understand the tradeoffs and constraints associated with such capabilities, as well as redundancy and diversity mechanisms that can be used to provide more predictable and reliable performance.
        	</t>
        	<section><name> 802.11 Managed network operation and admission control</name>
        	<t>
        		Time-sensitive applications and TSN standards are expected to operate under a managed network (e.g. industrial/enterprise network). Thus, the Wi-Fi operation must also be carefully managed and integrated with the overall TSN management framework, as defined in the <xref target='IEEE802.1Qcc'/> specification.
        	</t>
         	<t>
        		Some of the random-access latency and interference from legacy/unmanaged devices can be reduced under a centralized management mode as defined in <xref target='IEEE802.1Qcc'/>.
        	</t>
        	<t>
        		Existing traffic stream identification, configuration and admission control procedures defined in <xref target='IEEE80211'/> QoS mechanism can be re-used. However, given the high degree of determinism required by many time-sensitive applications, additional capabilities to manage interference and legacy devices within tight time-constraints need to be explored.
        	</t>
        	</section> <!-- 802.11 Managed network operation and admission control -->
        	<section><name>Scheduling for bounded latency and diversity</name>
        	<t>
        		As discussed earlier, the <xref target='IEEE80211ax'/> OFDMA mode introduces the possibility of assigning different RUs (time/frequency resources) to users within a PPDU. Several RU sizes are defined in the specification (26, 52, 106, 242, 484, 996 subcarriers). In addition, the AP can also decide on MCS (Modulation and Coding Scheme) and grouping of users within a given OFMDA PPDU. Such flexibility can be leveraged to support time-sensitive applications with bounded latency, especially in a managed network where stations can be configured to operate under the control of the AP, in a controlled environment (which contains only devices operating on the unlicensed band installed by the facility owner and where unexpected interference from other systems and/or radio access technologies only sporadically happens), or in a deployment where channel/link redundancy is used to reduce the impact of unmanaged devices/interference.
        	</t>
        	<t>
        		When the network is lightly loaded, it is possible to achieve latencies under 1 msec when Wi-Fi is operated in contention-based (i.e., without OFDMA) mode. It is also has been shown that it is possible to achieve 1 msec latencies in controlled environment with higher efficiency when multi-user transmissions are used (enabled by OFDMA operation)  <xref target='Cavalcanti_2019'/>. Obviously, there are latency, reliability and capacity tradeoffs to be considered. For instance, smaller RUs result in longer transmission durations, which may impact the minimal latency that can be achieved, but the contention latency and randomness elimination in an interference-free environment due to multi-user transmission is a major benefit of the OFDMA mode.
        	</t>
        	<t>
        		The flexibility to dynamically assign RUs to each transmission also enables the AP to provide frequency diversity, which can help increase reliability.
        	</t>
        	</section> <!--Scheduling for bounded latency and diversity-->
        </section> <!-- Applicability to deterministic flows -->
        </section><!-- 802.11ax High Efficiency (HE)   -->

        <section anchor="EHT"><name>802.11be Extreme High Throughput (EHT)</name>

        	<section><name>General Characteristics</name>
        		<t>
        			The ongoing <xref target='IEEE80211be'/>  project is the next major 802.11 amendment (after IEEE Std 802.11ax-2021) for operation in the 2.4, 5 and 6 GHz bands. 802.11be is expected to include new PHY and MAC features and it is targeting extremely high throughput (at least 30 Gbps), as well as enhancements to worst case latency and jitter. It is also expected to improve the integration with 802.1 TSN to support time-sensitive applications over Ethernet and Wireless LANs.
        			</t>
        		<t>
        			The 802.11be Task Group started its operation in May 2019, therefore, detailed information about specific features is not yet available. Only high level candidate features have been discussed so far, including:
        			</t><ol type='%d.'>
        				<li> 320MHz bandwidth and more efficient utilization of non-contiguous spectrum. </li>
        				<li> Multi-link operation. </li>
        				<li> 16 spatial streams and related MIMO enhancements. </li>
        				<li> Multi-Access Point (AP) Coordination.</li>
        				<li> Enhanced link adaptation and retransmission protocol, e.g. Hybrid Automatic Repeat Request (HARQ).</li>
        				<li> Any required adaptations to regulatory rules for the 6 GHz spectrum. </li>
        			</ol><t>
        		</t>
        	</section> <!-- General Characteristics-->
        	<section><name>Applicability to deterministic flows</name>
        		<t>
        			The 802.11 Real-Time Applications (RTA) Topic Interest Group (TIG) provided detailed information on use cases, issues and potential solution directions to improve support for time-sensitive applications in 802.11. The RTA TIG report <xref target='IEEE_doc_11-18-2009-06'/> was used as input to the 802.11be project scope.
        		</t>
        		<t>
        			Improvements for worst-case latency, jitter and reliability were the main topics identified in the RTA report, which were motivated by applications in gaming, industrial automation, robotics, etc. The RTA report also highlighted the need to support additional TSN capabilities, such as time-aware (802.1Qbv) shaping and packet replication and elimination as defined in 802.1CB.
        		</t>
        		<t>
        			802.11be is expected to build on and enhance 802.11ax capabilities to improve worst case latency and jitter. Some of the enhancement areas are discussed next.
        			</t>
        		<section><name>Enhanced scheduled operation for bounded latency </name>
        			<t>
        				In addition to the throughput enhancements, 802.11be will leverage the trigger-based scheduled operation enabled by 802.11ax to provide efficient and more predictable medium access. 802.11be is expected to include enhancements to reduce overhead and enable more efficient operation in managed network deployments <xref target='IEEE_doc_11-19-0373-00'/>.
        				</t>
        		</section> <!-- Enhanced scheduled operation for bounded latency -->
        		<section><name>Multi-AP coordination</name>
        			<t>
        				Multi-AP coordination is one of the main new candidate features in 802.11be. It can provide benefits in throughput and capacity and has the potential to address some of the issues that impact worst case latency and reliability.
        				Multi-AP coordination is expected to address the contention due to overlapping Basic Service Sets (OBSS), which is one of the main sources of random latency variations.
                        <!-- redundant with above
                        802.11be can define methods to enable better coordination between APs, for instance, in a managed network scenario, in order to reduce latency due to unmanaged contention. -->
	       			</t>

<t> Overall, multi-AP coordination algorithms consider three different phases:
 setup (where APs handling overlapping BSSs are assigned roles in a manual
 or automated way, e.g., coordinator and coordinated APs); coordination
 (where APs establish links among themselves, e.g., from a coordinating AP
 to coordinated APs; and then assign resources to served stations);
 transmission (where the coordinating APs optimize the distribution of the
 transmission opportunities).
	       			</t>


	       			<t>
	       				Several multi-AP coordination approaches have been discussed with different levels of complexities and benefits, but specific coordination methods have not yet been defined. Out of the different
 categories, MAC-driven examples include: coordinated OFDMA (Co-OFDMA);
 Coordinated TDMA (Co-TDMA); HARQ; whereas PHY-driven examples include:
 Coordinated Spatial Reuse (Co-SR) and Coordinated Beamforming (Co-BF).

	       			</t>
        		</section> <!-- Multi-AP coordination -->
        		<section><name>Multi-link operation</name>
        			<t>
        				802.11be will introduce new features to improve operation over multiple links and channels. By leveraging multiple links/channels, 802.11be can isolate time-sensitive traffic from network congestion, one of the main causes of large latency variations. In a managed 802.11be network, it should be possible to steer traffic to certain links/channels to isolate time-sensitive traffic from other traffic and help achieve bounded latency. The multi-link operation (MLO) has been already introduced in the 802.11be Draft and it can also enhance latency and reliability by enabling data frames to be duplicated across links.
        			</t>
        		</section> <!--Multi-link operation-->
        	</section>
        </section><!-- 802.11be Extreme High Throughput (EHT)  -->

        <section><name>802.11ad and 802.11ay (mmWave operation)</name>
        	<section><name>General Characteristics</name>
        		<t>
        			The IEEE 802.11ad amendment defines PHY and MAC capabilities to enable multi-Gbps throughput in the 60 GHz millimeter wave (mmWave) band. The standard addresses the adverse mmWave signal propagation characteristics and provides directional communication capabilities that take advantage of beamforming to cope with increased attenuation. An overview of the 802.11ad standard can be found in <xref target='Nitsche_2015'/>.
        		</t>
        		<t>
        			The IEEE 802.11ay is currently developing enhancements to the 802.11ad standard to enable the next generation mmWave operation targeting 100 Gbps throughput. Some of the main enhancements in 802.11ay include MIMO, channel bonding, improved channel access and beamforming training. An overview of the 802.11ay capabilities can be found in <xref target='Ghasempour_2017'/>.
        			</t>
        	</section><!--General Characteristics -->
        	<section><name>Applicability to deterministic flows</name>
        		<t>
        			The high data rates achievable with 802.11ad and 802.11ay can significantly reduce latency down to microsecond levels. Limited interference from legacy and other unlicensed devices in 60 GHz is also a benefit. However, directionality and short range typical in mmWave operation impose new challenges such as the overhead required for beam training and blockage issues, which impact both latency and reliability. Therefore, it is important to understand the use case and deployment conditions in order to properly apply and configure 802.11ad/ay networks for time sensitive applications.
        		</t>
        		<t>
        			The 802.11ad standard includes a scheduled access mode in which the central controller, after contending and reserving the channel for a dedicated period, can allocate to stations contention-free service periods. This scheduling capability is also available in 802.11ay, and it is one of the mechanisms that can be used to provide bounded latency to time-sensitive data flows in interference-free scenarios. An analysis of the theoretical latency bounds that can be achieved with 802.11ad service periods is provided in <xref target='Cavalcanti_2019'/>.
        		</t>
        	</section> <!-- Applicability to deterministic flows-->
        </section><!-- 802.11ad and 802.11ay (mmWave operation)  -->
   </section><!-- title="IEEE 802.11" -->


   <section><name>IEEE 802.15.4</name>

   <section><name>Provenance and Documents</name>
   <t>
   The IEEE802.15.4 Task Group has been driving the development of low-power
   low-cost radio technology.
   The IEEE802.15.4 physical layer has been designed to support demanding
   low-power scenarios targeting the use of unlicensed bands, both the 2.4 GHz
   and sub GHz Industrial, Scientific and Medical (ISM) bands. This has imposed
   requirements in terms of frame size, data rate and bandwidth to achieve
   reduced collision probability, reduced packet error rate, and acceptable
   range with limited transmission power. The PHY layer supports frames of up to
   127 bytes. The Medium Access Control (MAC) sublayer overhead is in the order
   of 10-20 bytes, leaving about 100 bytes to the upper layers. IEEE802.15.4
   uses spread spectrum modulation such as the Direct Sequence Spread
   Spectrum (DSSS).
   </t>

   <t>
   The Timeslotted Channel Hopping (TSCH) mode was added to the 2015 revision of
   the IEEE802.15.4 standard <xref target='IEEE802154'/>. TSCH is
   targeted at the embedded and industrial world, where reliability, energy
   consumption and cost drive the application space.
   </t>

   <!--  TSN-like activities, past and present (introduce the likes of as OFDMA, URLLC and EHT) -->
   <t>
   Time sensitive networking on low power constrained wireless networks, building on IEEE802.15.4,
   have been partially addressed by ISA100.11a <xref target='ISA100.11a'/> and
   WirelessHART <xref target='WirelessHART'/>. Both technologies
   involve a central controller that computes redundant paths for industrial
   process control traffic over a TSCH mesh. Moreover, ISA100.11a introduces
   IPv6 capabilities with a Link-Local Address for the join process and a
   global unicast addres for later exchanges, but the IPv6 traffic typically
   ends at a local application gateway and the full power of IPv6 for end-to-end
   communication is not enabled. 
   </t>

   <t>
   At the IETF, the 6TiSCH Working Group (WG) <xref target='TiSCH'/> deals with
   best effort operation of IPv6 <xref target='RFC8200'/> over TSCH. 6TiSCH has
   enabled distributed scheduling to exploit the deterministic
   access capabilities provided by TSCH. The group designed the essential
   mechanisms to enable the management plane operation while ensuring IPv6 is
   supported.
   </t>
   <t>
   6TiSCH defines the 6top layer, composed of one or more Scheduling Functions (SFs)
   and the 6top Protocol (6P Protocol) defined in RFC8480 <xref target='RFC8480'/>. 
   The 6P Protocol provides a pairwise negotiation mechanism to the control plane operation.
   The protocol supports agreement on a schedule between neighbors, enabling
   distributed scheduling.
   6P goes hand-in-hand with a Scheduling Function (SF), the policy that decides
   how to maintain cells and trigger 6P transactions. The Minimal Scheduling
   Function (MSF) <xref target='RFC9033'/> is the default SF defined
   by the 6TiSCH WG.
   With these mechanisms 6TiSCH can establish layer 2 links between neighbouring nodes and 
   support best effort traffic. RPL <xref target='RFC8480'/> provides the routing structure, 
   enabling the 6TiSCH devices to establish the links with well connected neighbours and thus
   forming the acyclic network graphs.   
   </t>

   <t>
   A Track at 6TiSCH is the application to wireless of the concept of a path in
   the <xref target='RFC8655'>"Detnet architecture"</xref>.
   A Track can follow a simple sequence of relay nodes or can be structured as a
   more complex Destination Oriented Directed Acyclic Graph (DODAG) to a unicast
   destination. Along a Track, 6TiSCH nodes reserve the resources to enable the
   efficient transmission of packets while aiming to optimize certain properties
   such as reliability and ensure small jitter or bounded latency. The Track
   structure enables Layer-2 forwarding schemes, reducing the overhead of taking
   routing decisions at the Layer-3.
   </t>
  
     <!--  DetNet-like arching art (introduce the likes of ISA100.11a or WiHART) -->
   <t>
   The 6TiSCH architecture <xref target='RFC9030'/>
   identifies different models to schedule resources along so-called Tracks
   (see <xref target='Tracks'/>) exploiting the
   TSCH schedule structure however the focus at 6TiSCH is on best effort traffic
   and the group was never chartered to produce standard work related to Tracks.
   </t>
   
   <t>
   There are several works that can be used to complement the overview provided in this document.
   For example <xref target='vilajosana21'/> provides a detailed description of the 6TiSCH protocols, 
   how they are linked together and how they are integrated to other standards like RPL and 6Lo.
   <xref target='morell13'/> introduces how label switching can be implemented in a TSCH network. 
   It proposes a policy to distribute labels in multihop network so as to enable differential services
   through the network paths. <xref target='dearmas16'/> presents an approach to improve network reliability
   at layer 3, considering and IEEE802.15.4 TSCH network and exploiting packet replication and path diversity 
   for that aim.
   </t>

   </section><!-- Provenance and Documents   -->


   <section><name>TimeSlotted Channel Hopping</name>


   <section><name>General Characteristics</name>
   <t>
   As a core technique in IEEE802.15.4, TSCH splits time in multiple time slots
   that repeat over time.
   A set of timeslots constructs a Slotframe (see
   <xref target='slotFrames'/>). For each
   timeslot, a set of available frequencies can be used, resulting in a
   matrix-like schedule (see <xref target='fig_slotframe'/>).
   </t>
<figure anchor='fig_slotframe'><name>Slotframe example with scheduled cells between nodes A, B and C</name>
<artwork><![CDATA[
                       timeslot offset
     | 0    1    2    3    4  | 0    1    2    3    4  |    Nodes
     +------------------------+------------------------+   +-----+
     |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |   |  C  |
CH-1 | EB |    |    |C->B|    | EB |    |    |C->B|    |   |     |
     |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |   +-----+
     +-------------------------------------------------+      |
     |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |      |
CH-2 |    |    |B->C|    |B->A|    |    |B->C|    |B->A|   +-----+
     |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |   |  B  |
     +-------------------------------------------------+   |     |
 ...                                                       +-----+
                                                              |
     +-------------------------------------------------+      |
     |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |   +-----+
CH-15|    |A->B|    |    |    |    |A->B|    |    |    |   |  A  |
     |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |   |     |
     +-------------------------------------------------+   +-----+
ch.
offset
Note: EB (Enhanced Beacon)
]]></artwork>
</figure>

   <t>
   The IEEE 802.15.4 TSCH standard does not define any scheduling mechanism but 
   only provides the architecture that establishes a slotted structure that can be 
   managed by a proper schedule. This schedule represents the possible communications of a node with its
   neighbors, and is managed by a Scheduling Function such as the Minimal
   Scheduling Function (MSF)  <xref target='RFC9033'/>. In MSF, each cell in
   the schedule is identified by its slotoffset and channeloffset coordinates. A
   cell's timeslot offset indicates its position in time, relative to the
   beginning of the slotframe. A cell's channel offset is an index which maps to
   a frequency at each iteration of the slotframe. Each packet exchanged between
   neighbors happens within one cell. The size of a cell is a timeslot duration,
   between 10 to 15 milliseconds. An Absolute Slot Number (ASN) indicates
   the number of slots elapsed since the network started. It increments at every
   slot. This is a 5 byte counter that can support networks running for more
   than 300 years without wrapping (assuming a 10 ms timeslot). Channel hopping
   provides increased reliability to multi-path fading and external
   interference. It is handled by TSCH through a channel hopping sequence
   referred as macHopSeq in the IEEE802.15.4 specification.
   </t>

   <t>
   <!-- bandwidth, beam forming-->
    The Time-Frequency Division Multiple Access provided by TSCH enables the
    orchestration of traffic flows, spreading them in time and frequency,
    and hence enabling an efficient management of the bandwidth utilization.
    Such efficient bandwidth utilization can be combined to OFDM modulations
    also supported by the IEEE802.15.4 standard <xref target='IEEE802154'/>
    since the 2015 version.
   </t>
   <t>
   <!-- spectrum -->
    TSCH networks operate in ISM bands in which the spectrum is shared by different coexisting technologies.
    Regulations such as FCC, ETSI and ARIB impose duty cycle regulations to limit the use of the bands but yet interference may constraint the probability to deliver a packet.
    Part of these reliability challenges are addressed at the MAC introducing redundancy and diversity, thanks to channel hopping, scheduling and ARQ policies.
    Yet, the MAC layer operates with a 1-hop vision, being limited to local actions to mitigate underperforming links.
    <!-- Pascal-> not sure if you want to mention here about the capability provided by RAW to determine the best path regardless of the performance of a particular link -->
   </t>
  
   </section> <!-- General Characteristics  -->

   <section><name>Applicability to Deterministic Flows</name>
   <t>
   <!-- expected capabilities for safety and automation, e.g., loops per second -->
    In the RAW context, low power reliable networks should address non-critical
    control scenarios such as Class 2 and monitoring scenarios such as Class 4
    defined by the RFC5673 <xref target='RFC5673'/>.
    As a low power technology targeting industrial scenarios radio transducers provide
    low data rates (typically between 50kbps to 250kbps) and robust modulations
    to trade-off performance to reliability. TSCH networks are organized in mesh
    topologies and connected to a backbone. Latency in the mesh network is
    mainly influenced by propagation aspects such as interference.
    ARQ methods and redundancy techniques such as replication and elimination
    should be studied to provide the needed performance to address deterministic
    scenarios.
   </t>

   <t>
    Nodes in a TSCH network are tightly synchronized. This enables building the
    slotted structure and ensures efficient utilization of resources thanks to
    proper scheduling policies. Scheduling is key to orchestrate the resources
    that different nodes in a Track or a path are using. Slotframes can be
    split in resource blocks reserving the needed capacity to certain flows.
    Periodic and bursty traffic can be handled independently in the schedule,
    using active and reactive policies and taking advantage of overprovisionned
    cells. Along a Track <xref target='Tracks'/>, resource blocks 
	can be chained so nodes in previous hops transmit their data before the next 
	packet comes.
    This provides a tight control to latency along a Track. Collision loss is
    avoided for best effort traffic by overprovisionning resources, giving time
    to the management plane of the network to dedicate more resources if needed.

      <!--

     -time synchronization
     - scheduling capabilities, discuss such things as Resource Units, time slots or resource blocks.
       Can we reserve periodic resources vs. ask each time, what precision can we get in latency control.
     - diversity scenarios, what's available,
     - gap analysis, e.g. discuss multihop, or what's missing how to do PAREO features.
     -->
   </t>
  
   

   <section anchor='detnet'><name>Centralized Path Computation</name>
   <t>
   When considering end-to-end communication over TSCH, a 6TiSCH device usually does 
   not place a request for bandwidth between itself and another device in the network.
   Rather, an Operation Control System (OCS) invoked through an Human/Machine Interface
  (HMI) provides the Traffic Specification, in particular in terms of latency
   and reliability, and the end nodes, to a Path Computation element (PCE).
   With this, the PCE computes a Track between the end nodes and provisions every
   hop in the Track with per-flow state that describes the per-hop operation for a
   given packet, the corresponding timeSlots, and the flow identification to
   recognize which packet is placed in which Track, sort out duplicates, etc.
   In <xref target='NorthSouth'/>, an example of Operational Control System and HMI
   is depicted.
   </t>
   <t>
   For a static configuration that serves a certain purpose for a long period of
   time, it is expected that a node will be provisioned in one shot with a full
   schedule, which incorporates the aggregation of its behavior for multiple
   Tracks. The 6TiSCH Architecture expects that the programing of the schedule
   is done over the Constrained Application Protocol (CoAP) as discussed in <xref target='I-D.ietf-6tisch-coap'>"6TiSCH
   Resource Management and Interaction using CoAP"</xref>.
   </t>
   <t>
   But an Hybrid mode may be required as well whereby a single Track is added,
   modified, or removed, for instance if it appears that a Track does not
   perform as expected.
   For that case, the expectation is that a protocol that flows along a Track
   (to be), in a fashion similar to classical Traffic Engineering (TE)
   <xref target='CCAMP'/>, may be used to update the state in the devices.
   In general that flow was not designed and it is expected that DetNet will determine the appropriate
   end-to-end protocols to be used in that case.
   </t>


<t keepWithNext='true'>Stream Management Entity</t><figure align='center' anchor='NorthSouth'>
<name>Architectural Layers</name>
    <artwork align='left'><![CDATA[

                      Operational Control System and HMI

   -+-+-+-+-+-+-+ Northbound -+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-

             PCE         PCE              PCE              PCE

   -+-+-+-+-+-+-+ Southbound -+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-

           --- 6TiSCH------6TiSCH------6TiSCH------6TiSCH--
  6TiSCH /     Device      Device      Device      Device   \
  Device-                                                    - 6TiSCH
         \     6TiSCH      6TiSCH      6TiSCH      6TiSCH   /  Device
           ----Device------Device------Device------Device--

			]]></artwork>
</figure>

   <section anchor='pmh'><name>Packet Marking and Handling</name>
   <t>
   Section "Packet Marking and Handling" of
   <xref target='RFC9030'/> describes the packet tagging and
   marking that is expected in 6TiSCH networks.
   </t>
   <section anchor='pmhft'><name>Tagging Packets for Flow Identification</name>
    <t>
     Packets that are routed by a PCE along a Track, are tagged to uniquely 
	 identify the Track and associated transmit bundle of timeSlots.
   </t>
   <t>
   It results that the tagging that is used for a DetNet flow outside the
   6TiSCH Low Power Lossy Network (LLN) must be swapped into 6TiSCH formats and back as the packet
   enters and then leaves the 6TiSCH network.
   </t>
   </section>

   <section anchor='pmhrre'><name>Replication, Retries and Elimination</name>
    <t>
       The 6TiSCH Architecture <xref target='RFC9030'/> leverages the Packet
       Replication, Retries, Elimination (PRE) and Ordering functions (PREOF), the
       precursor the PAREO functions in the RAW Architecture.

       PREF establishes several paths in a network to provide
       redundancy and parallel transmissions to bound the end-to-end delay.
       Considering the scenario shown in <xref target='fig_ladder'/>,
       many different paths are possible for S to reach R.
       A simple way to benefit from this topology could be to use the
       two independent paths via nodes A, C, E and via B, D, F.
       But more complex paths are possible as well.
    </t>

      <figure anchor='fig_ladder' align='center'><name>A Typical Ladder Shape with Two Parallel Paths Toward the Destination</name>
         <artwork align='center'><![CDATA[

                 (A)   (C)   (E)

   source (S)                       (R) (destination)

                 (B)   (D)   (F)

        ]]></artwork>
     </figure>

    <t>
    	By employing a Packet Replication function, each node forwards
        a copy of each data packet over two different branches.
        For instance, in <xref target='fig_replication'/>, the source node S
        transmits the data packet to nodes A and B, in two different
        timeslots within the same TSCH slotframe.
    </t>

        <figure anchor='fig_replication' align='center'><name>Packet Replication: S transmits twice the same data packet, to its Destination Parent (DP) (A) and to its Alternate Parent (AP) (B).</name>
            <artwork align='center'><![CDATA[

               ===> (A) => (C) => (E) ===
             //        \\//   \\//       \\
   source (S)          //\\   //\\         (R) (destination)
             \\       //  \\ //  \\      //
               ===> (B) => (D) => (F) ===

            ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

    <t>
        By employing Packet Elimination function once a node receives the
        first copy of a data packet, it discards the subsequent copies.
        Because the first copy that reaches a node is the
        one that matters, it is the only copy that will be
        forwarded upward.
    </t>

    <t>
		Considering that the wireless medium is broadcast by nature, any neighbor of
		a transmitter may overhear a transmission.
		By employing the Promiscuous Overhearing function, nodes will have multiple
		opportunities to receive a given data packet.
		For instance, in <xref target='fig_replication'/>, when the source node S
		transmits the data packet to node A, node B may overhear this transmission.
	</t>

   <t>
   6TiSCH expects elimination and replication of packets along a complex
   Track, but has no position about how the sequence numbers would be tagged in
   the packet.
   </t>
   <t>
   As it goes, 6TiSCH expects that timeSlots corresponding to copies
   of a same packet along a Track are correlated by configuration, and does not
   need to process the sequence numbers.
   </t>
   <t>
   The semantics of the configuration must enable correlated timeSlots to be
   grouped for transmit (and respectively receive) with 'OR' relations,
   and then an 'AND' relation must be configurable between groups.
   The semantics is that if the transmit (and respectively receive) operation
   succeeded in one timeSlot in an 'OR' group, then all the other timeslots in
   the group are ignored.
   Now, if there are at least two groups, the 'AND' relation between the groups
   indicates that one operation must succeed in each of the groups. Further details 
   can be found in the 6TiSCH Architecture document <xref target='RFC9030'/>.
   </t>
 <!--  
   <t>
   On the transmit side, timeSlots provisioned for retries along a same branch
   of a Track are placed a same'OR'group. The'OR'relation indicates that if
   a transmission is acknowledged, then further transmissions should not be
   attempted for timeSlots in that group. There are as many'OR'groups as
   there are branches of the Track departing from this node. Different'OR'groups
   are programmed for the purpose of replication, each group corresponding to
   one branch of the Track. The'AND'relation between the groups indicates that
   transmission over any of branches must be attempted regardless of whether a
   transmission succeeded in another branch. It is also possible to place cells
   to different next-hop routers in a same'OR'group. This allows to route along
   multi-path Tracks, trying one next-hop and then another only if sending to the
   first fails.
   </t>
   <t>
   On the receive side, all timeSlots are programmed in a same'OR'group.
   Retries of a same copy as well as converging branches for elimination
   are converged, meaning that the first successful reception is enough and that
   all the other timeSlots can be ignored.
   </t>
-->
   </section>
   </section>

   <section anchor='topo'><name>Topology and capabilities</name>


   <t>6TiSCH nodes are usually IoT devices, characterized by very limited amount
   of memory, just enough buffers to store one or a few IPv6 packets, and
   limited bandwidth between peers. It results that a node will maintain only a
   small number of peering information, and will not be able to store many
   packets waiting to be forwarded. Peers can be identified through MAC or IPv6
   addresses.
   </t>
   <t>
   Neighbors can be discovered over the radio using mechanism such as Enhanced Beacons,
   but, though the neighbor information is available in the 6TiSCH interface
   data model, 6TiSCH does not describe a protocol to pro-actively push the
   neighborhood information to a PCE.
   This protocol should be described and should operate over CoAP. The protocol
   should be able to carry multiple metrics, in particular the same metrics as
   used for RPL operations <xref target='RFC6551'/>.
   </t>
   <t>
   The energy that the device consumes in sleep, transmit and receive modes can
   be evaluated and reported. So can the amount of energy that is stored in the
   device and the power that it can be scavenged from the environment. The PCE
   should be able to compute Tracks that will implement policies on how the
   energy is consumed, for instance balance between nodes, ensure that the spent
   energy does not exceeded the scavenged energy over a period of time, etc...
   </t>


   </section>

   <section anchor='schd'><name>Schedule Management by a PCE</name>
      <t>
      6TiSCH supports a mixed model of centralized routes and distributed routes.
      Centralized routes can for example be computed by a entity such as a
      PCE <xref target='PCE'/>.
      Distributed routes are computed by <xref target='RFC6550'>RPL</xref>.
      </t>
      <t>
      Both methods may inject routes in the Routing Tables of the 6TiSCH routers.
      In either case, each route is associated with a 6TiSCH topology that can
      be a RPL Instance topology or a Track. The 6TiSCH topology is
      indexed by a Instance ID, in a format that reuses the RPLInstanceID as
      defined in RPL.
      </t>
      <t>
      Both RPL and PCE rely on shared sources such as policies to define Global
      and Local RPLInstanceIDs that can be used by either method. It is possible
      for centralized and distributed routing to share a same topology.
      Generally they will operate in different slotFrames, and centralized
      routes will be used for scheduled traffic and will have precedence over
      distributed routes in case of conflict between the slotFrames.
      </t>


   </section> <!--anchor="schd" title="Schedule Management by a PCE"-->


      <section anchor='slotFrames'><name>SlotFrames and Priorities</name>
         <t>A slotFrame is the base object that a PCE needs to manipulate
         to program a schedule into an LLN node. Elaboration on that concept
         can be found in section "SlotFrames and Priorities" of
         <xref target='RFC9030'/>.
         </t>
         <t>
         IEEE802.15.4 TSCH avoids contention on the medium by formatting time
         and frequencies in cells of transmission of equal duration.
         In order to describe that formatting of time and frequencies, the
         6TiSCH architecture defines a global concept that is called a Channel
         Distribution and Usage (CDU) matrix; a CDU matrix is a matrix of
         cells with an height equal to the number of available channels
         (indexed by ChannelOffsets) and a width (in timeSlots) that is the
         period of the network scheduling operation (indexed by slotOffsets) for
         that CDU matrix. The size of a cell is a timeSlot duration, and
         values  of 10 to 15 milliseconds are typical in 802.15.4 TSCH to
         accommodate for the transmission of a frame and an acknowledgement,
         including the security validation on the receive side which may take
         up to a few milliseconds on some device architecture.
         </t>
         <t>
         The frequency used by a cell in the matrix rotates in a pseudo-random
         fashion, from an initial position at an epoch time, as the matrix
         iterates over and over.
         </t>
         <t>
         A CDU matrix is computed by the PCE, but unallocated timeSlots may be
         used opportunistically by the nodes for classical best effort IP
         traffic. The PCE has precedence in the allocation in case of a conflict.
         </t>
         <t>
         In a given network, there might be multiple CDU matrices that operate
         with different width, so they have different durations and represent
         different periodic operations.
         It is recommended that all CDU matrices in a 6TiSCH domain operate with
         the same cell duration and are aligned, so as to reduce the
         chances of interferences from slotted-aloha operations.
         The PCE must compute the CDU matrices and shared that knowledge with
         all the nodes. The matrices are used in particular to define slotFrames.
          </t>
          <t>
          A slotFrame is a MAC-level abstraction that is common to all nodes and
          contains a series of timeSlots of equal length and precedence.
          It is characterized by a slotFrame_ID, and a slotFrame_size.
          A slotFrame aligns to a CDU matrix for its parameters, such as number
          and duration of timeSlots.
          </t>
          <t>
          Multiple slotFrames can coexist in a node schedule, i.e., a node can
          have multiple activities scheduled in different slotFrames, based on
          the precedence of the 6TiSCH topologies. The slotFrames may be
          aligned to different CDU matrices and thus have different width.
          There is typically one slotFrame for scheduled traffic that has the
          highest precedence and one or more slotFrame(s) for RPL traffic.
          The timeSlots in the slotFrame are indexed by the SlotOffset;
          the first cell is at SlotOffset 0.
          </t>
         <t>
         The 6TiSCH architecture introduces the concept of chunks
         (<xref target='RFC9030'/>) to operate
         such spectrum distribution for a whole group of cells at a time.
         The CDU matrix is formatted into a set of chunks, each of them
         identified uniquely by a chunk-ID, see <xref target='fig3'/>.
         The PCE must compute the partitioning of CDU matrices into chunks and
         shared that knowledge with all the nodes in a 6TiSCH network.
         </t>
            <figure anchor='fig3'><name>CDU matrix Partitioning in Chunks</name>
<artwork>
<![CDATA[
             +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+     +-----+
chan.Off. 0  |chnkA|chnkP|chnk7|chnkO|chnk2|chnkK|chnk1| ... |chnkZ|
             +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+     +-----+
chan.Off. 1  |chnkB|chnkQ|chnkA|chnkP|chnk3|chnkL|chnk2| ... |chnk1|
             +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+     +-----+
               ...
             +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+     +-----+
chan.Off. 15 |chnkO|chnk6|chnkN|chnk1|chnkJ|chnkZ|chnkI| ... |chnkG|
             +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+     +-----+
                0     1     2     3     4     5     6          M
]]>
</artwork>
            </figure>
         <t>
            The appropriation of a chunk can be requested explicitly by the
            PCE to any node. After a successful appropriation, the PCE owns the
            cells in that chunk, and may use them as hard cells to set up Tracks.
            Then again, 6TiSCH did not propose a method for chunk
            definition and a protocol for appropriation. This is to be done
            at RAW.
         </t>
      </section>

   </section>
   <section anchor='Tracks'><name>6TiSCH Tracks</name>

   <t>
   A Track at 6TiSCH is the application to wireless of the concept of a path in
   the <xref target='RFC8655'>"Detnet architecture"</xref>.
   A Track can follow a simple sequence of relay nodes or can be structured as a
   more complex Destination Oriented Directed Acyclic Graph (DODAG) to a unicast
   destination. Along a Track, 6TiSCH nodes reserve the resources to enable the
   efficient transmission of packets while aiming to optimize certain properties
   such as reliability and ensure small jitter or bounded latency. The Track
   structure enables Layer-2 forwarding schemes, reducing the overhead of taking
   routing decisions at the Layer-3.
   </t>
   <t>
   Serial Tracks can be understood as the concatenation of cells or bundles
   along a routing path from a source towards a destination. The serial Track
   concept is analogous to the circuit concept where resources are chained
   through the multi-hop topology. For example, A bundle of Tx Cells in a
   particular node is paired to a bundle of Rx Cells in the next hop node
   following a routing path.
   </t>
   <t>
   Whereas scheduling ensures reliable delivery in bounded time along any Track,
   high availability requires the application of PAREO functions along a more
   complex DODAG Track structure. A DODAG has forking and joining nodes where
   the concepts such as Replication and Elimination can be exploited.
   Spatial redundancy increases the overall energy consumption in the network but
   improves significantly the availability of the network as well as the packet
   delivery ratio.

   A Track may also branch off and rejoin, for the purpose of the so-called
   Packet Replication and Elimination (PRE), over non congruent branches.
   PRE may be used to complement layer-2 Automatic Repeat reQuest (ARQ) and
   receiver-end Ordering to form the PAREO functions. PAREO functions enable
   to meet industrial expectations in PDR within bounded delivery time over a
   Track that includes wireless links, even when the Track extends beyond the
   6TiSCH network.
      </t>
   <t>The RAW Track described in the RAW Architecture
   <xref target='I-D.ietf-raw-architecture'/> inherits directly from that model.
   RAW extends the graph beyond a DODAG as long as a given packet cannot loop
   within the Track.
   </t>
         <figure anchor='fig4'><name>End-to-End deterministic Track</name>
<artwork><![CDATA[

                  +-----+
                  | IoT |
                  | G/W |
                  +-----+
                     ^  <---- Elimination
                    | |
     Track branch   | |
            +-------+ +--------+ Subnet Backbone
            |                  |
         +--|--+            +--|--+
         |  |  | Backbone   |  |  | Backbone
    o    |  |  | router     |  |  | router
         +--/--+            +--|--+
    o     /    o     o---o----/       o
        o    o---o--/   o      o   o  o   o
   o     \  /     o               o   LLN    o
      o   v  <---- Replication
          o


]]></artwork>
         </figure>
      <t>In the example above (see <xref target='fig4'/>), a Track is laid out
      from a field device in a 6TiSCH network to an IoT gateway that is located
      on a IEEE802.1 TSN backbone.
      </t>
      <t>
      The Replication function in the field device sends a copy of each packet
      over two different branches, and a PCE schedules each hop of both branches
      so that the two
      copies arrive in due time at the gateway. In case of a loss on one branch,
      hopefully the other copy of the packet still makes it in due time. If two
      copies make it to the IoT gateway, the Elimination function in the gateway
      ignores the extra packet and presents only one copy to upper layers.
      </t>
      <t>
      At each 6TiSCH hop along the Track, the PCE may schedule more than one
      timeSlot for a packet, so as to support Layer-2 retries (ARQ). It is also
      possible that the field device only uses the second branch if sending over
      the first branch fails.
      </t>
      <t>
      In current deployments, a TSCH Track does not necessarily support PRE but
      is systematically multi-path. This means that a Track is scheduled so as
      to ensure that each hop has at least two forwarding solutions, and the
      forwarding decision is to try the preferred one and use the other in
      case of Layer-2 transmission failure as detected by ARQ.
         </t>
           <t>Methods to implement complex Tracks are described
   in <xref target='I-D.papadopoulos-paw-pre-reqs'/> and complemented by
   extensions to the RPL routing protocol in
   <xref target='I-D.ietf-roll-nsa-extension'/> for best effort traffic, but a
   centralized routing technique such as promoted in DetNet is still missing.

      </t>
     <section anchor='Tschd'><name>Track Scheduling Protocol</name>
      <t>
         Section "Schedule Management Mechanisms" of the 6TiSCH architecture
         describes 4 paradigms to manage the TSCH schedule of the LLN nodes:
         Static Scheduling, neighbor-to-neighbor Scheduling, remote monitoring
         and scheduling management, and Hop-by-hop scheduling.
         The Track operation for DetNet corresponds to a remote monitoring and
         scheduling management by a PCE.
      </t>
      <t>
      Early work at 6TiSCH on a data model and a protocol to program the
      schedule in the 6TiSCH device was never concluded as the group focussed on
      best effort traffic. This work would be revived by RAW:
      </t>
      <ul empty='true' spacing='normal'>
         <li>
            The 6top interface document
            <xref target='RFC8480'/>
            (to be reopened at RAW) was intended to
            specify the generic data model that can be used to monitor and
            manage
            resources of the 6top sublayer. Abstract methods were suggested
            for use
            by a management entity in the device. The data model also enables
            remote control operations on the 6top sublayer.
         </li>
         <li>
            <xref target='I-D.ietf-6tisch-coap'/>
            (to be reopened at RAW) was intended to define a mapping of the 6top
            set of commands, which is described in RFC 8480, to CoAP resources.
            This allows an entity to interact with the 6top layer of a node that
            is multiple hops away in a RESTful fashion.
         </li>
         <li>
            <xref target='I-D.ietf-6tisch-coap'/> also defined a basic set CoAP
            resources and associated RESTful access methods
            (GET/PUT/POST/DELETE). The payload (body) of the CoAP messages
            is encoded using the CBOR format.
            The PCE commands are expected to be issued directly as CoAP requests
            or to be mapped back and forth into CoAP by a gateway function at
            the edge of the 6TiSCH network. For instance, it is possible that a
            mapping entity on the backbone transforms a non-CoAP protocol such
            as PCEP into the RESTful interfaces that the 6TiSCH devices support.
          </li>
       </ul>
   </section>






   <section anchor='fwd'><name>Track Forwarding</name>
      <t>
         By forwarding, this specification means the per-packet operation that
         allows to deliver a packet to a next hop or an upper layer in this node.
         Forwarding is based on pre-existing state that was installed as a
         result of the routing computation of a Track by a PCE.
         The 6TiSCH architecture supports three different forwarding model,
         G-MPLS Track Forwarding (TF), 6LoWPAN Fragment Forwarding (FF) and
         IPv6 Forwarding (6F) which is the classical IP operation
         <xref target='RFC9030'/>.
         The DetNet case relates to the Track Forwarding operation under the
         control of a PCE.
      </t>
         <t>
            A Track is a unidirectional path between a source and a destination.
            In a Track cell, the normal operation of IEEE802.15.4
            Automatic Repeat-reQuest (ARQ) usually happens, though the
            acknowledgment may be omitted in some cases, for instance if there
            is no scheduled cell for a retry.
         </t>
         <t>
            Track Forwarding is the simplest and fastest. A bundle of cells set
            to receive (RX-cells) is uniquely paired to a bundle of cells that
            are set to transmit (TX-cells), representing a layer-2 forwarding
            state that can be used regardless of the network layer protocol.
            This model can effectively be seen as a Generalized Multi-protocol
            Label Switching (G-MPLS) operation in that the information used to

            switch a frame is not an explicit label, but rather related to other
            properties of the way the packet was received, a particular cell in
            the case of 6TiSCH.
            As a result, as long as the TSCH MAC (and Layer-2 security) accepts
            a frame, that frame can be switched regardless of the protocol,
            whether this is an IPv6 packet, a 6LoWPAN fragment, or a frame from
            an alternate protocol such as WirelessHART or ISA100.11a.
         </t>
         <t>
            A data frame that is forwarded along a Track normally has
            a destination MAC address that is set to broadcast -
            or a multicast address depending on MAC support.
            This way, the MAC layer in the intermediate nodes accepts the
            incoming frame and 6top switches it without incurring a change in
            the MAC header. In the case of IEEE802.15.4, this means effectively
            broadcast, so that along the Track the short address for the
            destination of the frame is set to 0xFFFF.
         </t>
         <t>
            A Track is thus formed end-to-end as a succession of paired bundles,
            a receive bundle from the previous hop and   a transmit bundle to
            the next hop along the Track, and a cell in such a bundle belongs to
            at most one Track.
            For a given iteration of the device schedule, the effective channel
            of the cell is obtained by adding a pseudo-random number to the
            channelOffset of the cell, which results in a rotation of the
            frequency that used for transmission.
            The bundles may be computed so as to accommodate both variable rates
            and retransmissions, so they might not be fully used at a given
            iteration of the schedule.
            The 6TiSCH architecture provides additional means to avoid waste of
            cells as well as overflows in the transmit bundle, as follows:
         </t>
         <t>
            In one hand, a TX-cell that is not needed for the current iteration
            may be reused opportunistically on a per-hop basis for routed
            packets.
            When all of the frame that were received for a given Track are
            effectively transmitted, any available TX-cell for that Track
            can be reused for upper layer traffic for which the next-hop router
            matches the next hop along the Track. In that case, the cell
            that is being used is effectively a TX-cell from the Track, but the
            short address for the destination is that of the next-hop router.
            It results that a frame that is received in a RX-cell of a Track
            with a destination MAC address set to this node as opposed to
            broadcast must be extracted from the Track and delivered to the
            upper layer (a frame with an unrecognized MAC address is dropped at
            the lower MAC layer and thus is not received at the 6top sublayer).
         </t>
         <t>On the other hand, it might happen that there are not enough
            TX-cells in the transmit bundle to accommodate the Track traffic,
            for instance if more retransmissions are needed than provisioned.
            In that case, the frame can be placed for transmission in the
            bundle that is used for layer-3 traffic towards the next hop along
            the Track as long as it can be routed by the upper layer, that is,
            typically, if the frame transports an IPv6 packet. The MAC address
            should be set to the next-hop MAC address to avoid confusion.
            It results that a frame that is received over a layer-3 bundle may
            be in fact associated to a Track. In a classical IP link such as an
            Ethernet, off-Track traffic is typically in excess over reservation
            to be routed along the non-reserved path based on its QoS setting.
            But with 6TiSCH, since the use of the layer-3 bundle may be due to
            transmission failures, it makes sense for the receiver to recognize
            a frame that should be re-Tracked, and to place it back on the
            appropriate bundle if possible.
            A frame should be re-Tracked if the Per-Hop-Behavior
            group indicated in the Differentiated Services Field in the
            IPv6 header is set to Deterministic Forwarding, as discussed in
            <xref target='pmh'/>.
            A frame is re-Tracked by scheduling it for transmission over the
            transmit bundle associated to the Track,
            with the destination MAC address set to broadcast.
         </t>
         <t>
            There are 2 modes for a Track, transport mode and tunnel mode.
         </t>
         <section><name>Transport Mode</name>
            <t>
               In transport mode, the Protocol Data Unit (PDU) is associated
               with flow-dependant meta-data that refers uniquely to the Track,
               so the 6top sublayer can place the frame in the appropriate cell
               without ambiguity. In the case of IPv6 traffic, this flow
               identification is transported in the Flow Label of the IPv6
               header.
               Associated with the source IPv6 address, the Flow Label forms a
               globally unique identifier for that particular Track that is
               validated at egress before restoring
               the destination MAC address (DMAC) and punting to the upper layer.
            </t>
               <figure anchor='fig5'><name>Track Forwarding, Transport Mode</name>
<artwork><![CDATA[
                       |                                    ^
   +--------------+    |                                    |
   |     IPv6     |    |                                    |
   +--------------+    |                                    |
   |  6LoWPAN HC  |    |                                    |
   +--------------+  ingress                              egress
   |     6top     |   sets     +----+          +----+     restores
   +--------------+  dmac to   |    |          |    |     dmac to
   |   TSCH MAC   |   brdcst   |    |          |    |      self
   +--------------+    |       |    |          |    |       |
   |   LLN PHY    |    +-------+    +--...-----+    +-------+
   +--------------+
]]></artwork>
               </figure>
         </section>
         <section><name>Tunnel Mode</name>
            <t>
               In tunnel mode, the frames originate from an arbitrary protocol
               over a compatible MAC that may or may not be synchronized with
               the 6TiSCH network. An example of this would be a router with a
               dual radio that is capable of receiving and sending WirelessHART
               or ISA100.11a frames with the second radio, by presenting
               itself as an Access Point or a Backbone Router, respectively.
            </t>
            <t>
               In that mode, some entity (e.g. PCE) can coordinate with a
               WirelessHART Network Manager or an ISA100.11a System Manager to
               specify the flows that are to be transported transparently
               over the Track.
            </t>
               <figure anchor='fig6'><name>Track Forwarding, Tunnel Mode</name>
<artwork><![CDATA[
   +--------------+
   |     IPv6     |
   +--------------+
   |  6LoWPAN HC  |
   +--------------+             set            restore
   |     6top     |            +dmac+          +dmac+
   +--------------+          to|brdcst       to|nexthop
   |   TSCH MAC   |            |    |          |    |
   +--------------+            |    |          |    |
   |   LLN PHY    |    +-------+    +--...-----+    +-------+
   +--------------+    |   ingress                 egress   |
                       |                                    |
   +--------------+    |                                    |
   |   LLN PHY    |    |                                    |
   +--------------+    |                                    |
   |   TSCH MAC   |    |                                    |
   +--------------+    | dmac =                             | dmac =
   |ISA100/WiHART |    | nexthop                            v nexthop
   +--------------+
]]></artwork>
               </figure>
            <t>
               In that case, the flow information that identifies the Track at
               the ingress 6TiSCH router is derived from the RX-cell. The dmac
               is set to this node but the flow information indicates that the
               frame must be tunneled over a particular Track so the frame is
               not passed to the upper layer. Instead, the dmac is forced to
               broadcast and the frame is passed to the 6top sublayer for switching.
            </t>
            <t>
               At the egress 6TiSCH router, the reverse operation occurs. Based
               on metadata associated to the Track, the frame is passed to the
               appropriate link layer with the destination MAC restored.
            </t>
         </section>
         <section><name>Tunnel Metadata</name>
            <t>
               Metadata coming with the Track configuration is expected to provide the destination MAC address
               of the egress endpoint as well as the tunnel mode and specific data depending on the mode,
               for instance a service access point for frame delivery at egress.
               If the tunnel egress point does not have a MAC address that matches the configuration,
               the Track installation fails.
            </t>
            <t>
               In transport mode, if the final layer-3 destination is the tunnel termination, then it is possible
               that the IPv6 address of the destination is compressed at the 6LoWPAN sublayer based on the MAC address.
               It is thus mandatory at the ingress point to validate that the MAC address that was used at the 6LoWPAN
               sublayer for compression matches that of the tunnel egress point. For that reason, the node that injects
               a packet on a Track checks that the destination is effectively that of the tunnel egress point
               before it overwrites it to broadcast.
               The 6top sublayer at the tunnel egress point reverts that operation to the MAC address obtained
               from the tunnel metadata.
            </t>

          </section>
         <section><name>OAM</name>
            <t>

	        <xref target='RFC7276'> An Overview of Operations,
            Administration, and Maintenance (OAM) Tools</xref> provides an
            overwiew of the existing tooling for OAM <xref target='RFC6291'/>. Tracks are complex paths and new tooling
            is necessary to manage them, with respect to load control, timing,
            and the Packet Replication and Elimination Functions (PREF).

            </t>
            <t>
            An example of such tooling can be found in the context of
            <xref target='RFC8279'>BIER</xref> and more specifically
            <xref target='RFC9262'>BIER Traffic Engineering</xref>
            (BIER-TE):
            <xref target='I-D.thubert-bier-replication-elimination'/>
            leverages BIER-TE to control the process of PREF, and to provide
            traceability of these operations, in the deterministic dataplane,
            along a complex Track.
            For the 6TiSCH type of constrained environment,
            <xref target='I-D.thubert-6lo-bier-dispatch'/> enables an efficient
            encoding of the BIER bitmap within the 6LoRH framework.
            </t>

   </section>
   </section>

   </section> <!-- 6TiSCH Tracks  -->


   </section><!-- Applicability to deterministic flows  -->

   </section> <!-- IEEE 802.15.4  -->
   </section> <!-- TimeSlotted Channel Hopping-->



   <section><name>5G</name>

   <section><name>Provenance and Documents</name>
   <t>
   The 3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP) incorporates many companies
   whose business is related to cellular network operation as well as network
   equipment and device manufacturing. All generations of 3GPP technologies
   provide scheduled wireless segments, primarily in licensed spectrum which is
   beneficial for reliability and availability.
   </t>

   <t>
   In 2016, the 3GPP started to design New Radio (NR) technology belonging to
   the fifth generation (5G) of cellular networks. NR has been designed from
   the beginning to not only address enhanced Mobile Broadband (eMBB) services
   for consumer devices such as smart phones or tablets but is also tailored
   for future Internet of Things (IoT) communication and connected
   cyber-physical systems. In addition to eMBB, requirement categories have
   been defined on Massive Machine-Type Communication (M-MTC) for a large
   number of connected devices/sensors, and Ultra-Reliable Low-Latency
   Communication (URLLC) for connected control systems and critical
   communication as illustrated in <xref target='fig-5g-triangle'/>. It is
   the URLLC capabilities that make 5G a great candidate for reliable
   low-latency communication. With these three corner stones, NR is a complete
   solution supporting the connectivity needs of consumers, enterprises, and
   public sector for both wide area and local area, e.g. indoor deployments.
   A general overview of NR can be found in <xref target='TS38300'/>.
   </t>

<figure anchor='fig-5g-triangle'><name>5G Application Areas</name>
<artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
            enhanced
        Mobile Broadband
               ^
              / \
             /   \
            /     \
           /       \
          /   5G    \
         /           \
        /             \
       /               \
      +-----------------+
   Massive          Ultra-Reliable
 Machine-Type        Low-Latency
Communication       Communication
]]></artwork>
</figure>

   <t>
   As a result of releasing the first NR specification in 2018 (Release 15), it
   has been proven by many companies that NR is a URLLC-capable technology and
   can deliver data packets at 10^-5 packet error rate within 1ms latency
   budget <xref target='TR37910'/>. Those evaluations were consolidated and
   forwarded to ITU to be included in the <xref target='IMT2020'/> work.
   </t>

   <t>
   In order to understand communication requirements for automation in vertical
   domains, 3GPP studied different use cases <xref target='TR22804'/> and
   released technical specification with reliability, availability and latency
   demands for a variety of applications <xref target='TS22104'/>.
   </t>

   <t>
   As an evolution of NR, multiple studies have been conducted in scope of 3GPP
   Release 16 including the following two, focusing on radio aspects:
   </t><ol type='%d.'>
      <li> Study on physical layer enhancements for NR ultra-reliable and low
	  latency communication (URLLC) <xref target='TR38824'/>.</li>
      <li> Study on NR industrial Internet of Things (I-IoT)
	  <xref target='TR38825'/>.</li>
     </ol><t>
   </t>

   <t>
   Resulting of these studies, further enhancements to NR have been standardized
   in 3GPP Release 16, hence, available in <xref target='TS38300'/>, and
   continued in 3GPP Release 17 standardization (according to <xref target='RP210854'/>).
   </t>

   <t>

   In addition, several enhancements have been done on system architecture level
   which are reflected in System architecture for the 5G System (5GS)
   <xref target='TS23501'/>.
   These enhancements include multiple features in  support of Time-Sensitive
   Communications (TSC) by Release 16 and Release 17. Further improvements are
   provided in Release 18,  e.g., support for DetNet <xref target='TR2370046'/>.

   </t>

   <t>
   The adoption and the use of 5G is facilitated by multiple organizations. For
   instance, the 5G Alliance for Connected Industries and Automation (5G-ACIA)
   brings together widely varying 5G stakeholders including Information and
   Communication Technology (ICT) players and Operational Technology (OT)
   companies, e.g.: industrial automation enterprises, machine builders, and
   end users. Another example is the 5G Automotive Association (5GAA), which
   bridges ICT and automotive technology companies to develop end-to-end
   solutions for future mobility and transportation services.
   </t>

   </section><!-- Provenance and Documents   -->



   <section><name>General Characteristics</name>

   <t>
   The 5G Radio Access Network (5G RAN) with its NR interface includes several
   features to achieve Quality of Service (QoS), such as a guaranteeably
   low latency or tolerable packet error rates for selected data flows.
   Determinism is achieved by centralized admission control and scheduling of
   the wireless frequency resources, which are typically licensed frequency
   bands assigned to a network operator.
   </t>

   <t>
   NR enables short transmission slots in a radio subframe, which benefits
   low-latency applications. NR also introduces mini-slots, where prioritized
   transmissions can be started without waiting for slot boundaries, further
   reducing latency. As part of giving priority and faster radio access to
   URLLC traffic, NR introduces preemption where URLLC data transmission can
   preempt ongoing non-URLLC transmissions. Additionally, NR applies very fast
   processing, enabling retransmissions even within short latency bounds.
   </t>

   <t>
   NR defines extra-robust transmission modes for increased reliability both
   for data and control radio channels. Reliability is further improved by
   various techniques, such as multi-antenna transmission, the use of multiple
   frequency carriers in parallel and packet duplication over independent radio
   links. NR also provides full mobility support, which is an important
   reliability aspect not only for devices that are moving, but also for
   devices located in a changing environment.
   </t>

   <t>
   Network slicing is seen as one of the key features for 5G, allowing vertical
   industries to take advantage of 5G networks and services. Network slicing is
   about transforming a Public Land Mobile Network (PLMN) from a single network
   to a network where logical partitions are created, with appropriate network
   isolation, resources, optimized topology and specific configuration to serve
   various service requirements. An operator can configure and manage the
   mobile network to support various types of services enabled by 5G, for
   example eMBB and URLLC, depending on the different customers needs.
   </t>

   <t>
   Exposure of capabilities of 5G Systems to the network or applications
   outside the 3GPP domain have been added to Release 16
   <xref target='TS23501'/>. Via exposure interfaces, applications can access
   5G capabilities, e.g., communication service monitoring and network
   maintenance.
   </t>

   <t>
   For several generations of mobile networks, 3GPP has considered how the
   communication system should work on a global scale with billions of users,
   taking into account resilience aspects, privacy regulation, protection of
   data, encryption, access and core network security, as well as interconnect.
   Security requirements evolve as demands on trustworthiness increase. For
   example, this has led to the introduction of enhanced privacy protection
   features in 5G. 5G also employs strong security algorithms, encryption of
   traffic, protection of signaling and protection of interfaces.
   </t>

   <t>
   One particular strength of mobile networks is the authentication, based on
   well-proven algorithms and tightly coupled with a global identity management
   infrastructure. Since 3G, there is also mutual authentication, allowing the
   network to authenticate the device and the device to authenticate the
   network. Another strength is secure solutions for storage and distribution
   of keys fulfilling regulatory requirements and allowing international
   roaming. When connecting to 5G, the user meets the entire communication
   system, where security is the result of standardization, product security,
   deployment, operations and management as well as incident handling
   capabilities. The mobile networks approach the entirety in a rather
   coordinated fashion which is beneficial for security.
   </t>

   </section><!-- General Characteristics   -->


   <section><name>Deployment and Spectrum</name>

   <t>
   The 5G system allows deployment in a vast spectrum range, addressing
   use-cases in both wide-area as well as local networks. Furthermore, 5G can
   be configured for public and non-public access.
   </t>

   <t>
   When it comes to spectrum, NR allows combining the merits of many frequency
   bands, such as the high bandwidths in millimeter Waves (mmW) for extreme
   capacity locally, as well as the broad coverage when using mid- and low
   frequency bands to address wide-area scenarios. URLLC is achievable in all
   these bands. Spectrum can be either licensed, which means that the license
   holder is the only authorized user of that spectrum range, or unlicensed,
   which means that anyone who wants to use the spectrum can do so.
   </t>

   <t>
   A prerequisite for critical communication is performance predictability,
   which can be achieved by the full control of the access to the spectrum,
   which 5G provides. Licensed spectrum guarantees control over spectrum usage
   by the system, making it a preferable option for critical communication.
   However, unlicensed spectrum can provide an additional resource for scaling
   non-critical communications. While NR is initially developed for usage of
   licensed spectrum, the functionality to access also unlicensed spectrum was
   introduced in 3GPP Release 16. Moreover, URLLC features are enhanced in
   Release 17 <xref target='RP210854'/> to be better applicable to unlicensed
   spectrum.
   </t>

   <t>
   Licensed spectrum dedicated to mobile communications has been allocated to
   mobile service providers, i.e. issued as longer-term licenses by national
   administrations around the world. These licenses have often been associated
   with coverage requirements and issued across whole countries, or in large
   regions. Besides this, configured as a non-public network (NPN) deployment,
   5G can provide network services also to a non-operator defined organization
   and its premises such as a factory deployment. By this isolation, quality of
   service requirements, as well as security requirements can be achieved. An
   integration with a public network, if required, is also possible. The
   non-public (local) network can thus be interconnected with a public network,
   allowing devices to roam between the networks.
   </t>

   <t>
   In an alternative model, some countries are now in the process of allocating
   parts of the 5G spectrum for local use to industries. These non-service
   providers then have a choice of applying for a local license themselves and
   operating their own network or cooperating with a public network operator or
   service provider.
   </t>

   </section><!-- Deployment and Spectrum   -->


   <section><name>Applicability to Deterministic Flows</name>

   <section><name>System Architecture</name>

   <t>
   The 5G system <xref target='TS23501'/> consists of the User Equipment (UE)
   at the terminal side, and the Radio Access Network (RAN) with the gNB as
   radio base station node, as well as the Core Network (CN), which is connected
   to the external Data Network (DN). The core network is based on a service-based
   architecture with the central functions: Access and Mobility Management
   Function (AMF), Session Management Function (SMF) and User Plane Function (UPF)
   as illustrated in <xref target='fig-5g-arch'/>. "(Note that this document only
   explains key functions, however, <xref target='fig-5g-arch'/> provides a more
   detailed view.)"
   </t>

   <t>The gNBs main responsibility is the radio resource management, including
   admission control and scheduling, mobility control and radio measurement
   handling. The AMF handles the UEs connection status and security, while the
   SMF controls the UEs data sessions. The UPF handles the user plane traffic.
   </t>

   <t>The SMF can instantiate various Packet Data Unit (PDU) sessions for the
   UE, each associated with a set of QoS flows, i.e., with different QoS
   profiles. Segregation of those sessions is also possible, e.g., resource
   isolation in the RAN and in the CN can be defined (slicing).
   </t>

<figure anchor='fig-5g-arch'><name>5G System Architecture</name>
<artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
  +----+  +---+   +---+    +---+    +---+   +---+
  |NSSF|  |NEF|   |NRF|    |PCF|    |UDM|   |AF |
  +--+-+  +-+-+   +-+-+    +-+-+    +-+-+   +-+-+
     |      |       |        |        |       |
Nnssf|  Nnef|   Nnrf|    Npcf|    Nudm|    Naf|
     |      |       |        |        |       |
  ---+------+-+-----+-+------------+--+-----+-+---
              |       |            |         |
         Nausf|  Nausf|        Nsmf|         |
              |       |            |         |
           +--+-+   +-+-+        +-+-+     +-+-+
           |AUSF|   |AMF|        |SMF|     |SCP|
           +----+   +++-+        +-+-+     +---+
                    / |            |
                   /  |            |
                  /   |            |
                 N1   N2           N4
                /     |            |
               /      |            |
              /       |            |
          +--+-+   +--+--+      +--+---+      +----+
          | UE +---+(R)AN+--N3--+ UPF  +--N6--+ DN |
          +----+   +-----+      ++----++      +----+
                                 |    |
                                 +-N9-+
]]></artwork>
</figure>

   <t>
   To allow UE mobility across cells/gNBs, handover mechanisms are supported in
   NR. For an established connection, i.e., connected mode mobility, a gNB can
   configure a UE to report measurements of received signal strength and
   quality of its own and neighbouring cells, periodically or event-based.
   Based on these measurement reports, the gNB decides to handover a UE to
   another target cell/gNB. Before triggering the handover, it is hand-shaked
   with the target gNB based on network signalling. A handover command is then
   sent to the UE and the UE switches its connection to the target cell/gNB.
   The Packet Data Convergence Protocol (PDCP) of the UE can be configured to
   avoid data loss in this procedure, i.e., handle retransmissions if needed.
   Data forwarding is possible between source and target gNB as well. To
   improve the mobility performance further, i.e., to avoid connection failures,
   e.g., due to too-late handovers, the mechanism of conditional handover is
   introduced in Release 16 specifications. Therein a conditional handover
   command, defining a triggering point, can be sent to the UE before UE enters
   a handover situation. A further improvement that has been introduced in
   Release 16 is the Dual Active Protocol Stack (DAPS), where the UE maintains
   the connection to the source cell while connecting to the target cell. This
   way, potential interruptions in packet delivery can be avoided entirely.
   </t>

   </section><!-- System Architecture   -->


   <section><name>Overview of The Radio Protocol Stack</name>

   <t>
   The protocol architecture for NR consists of the L1 Physical layer (PHY) and
   as part of the L2, the sublayers of Medium Access Control (MAC), Radio Link
   Control (RLC), Packet Data Convergence Protocol (PDCP), as well as the
   Service Data Adaption Protocol (SDAP).
   </t>

   <t>
   The PHY layer handles signal processing related actions, such as
   encoding/decoding of data and control bits, modulation, antenna precoding
   and mapping.
   </t>

   <t>
   The MAC sub-layer handles multiplexing and priority handling of logical
   channels (associated with QoS flows) to transport blocks for PHY
   transmission, as well as scheduling information reporting and error
   correction through Hybrid Automated Repeat Request (HARQ).
   </t>

   <t>
   The RLC sublayer handles sequence numbering of higher layer packets,
   retransmissions through Automated Repeat Request (ARQ), if configured, as
   well as segmentation and reassembly and duplicate detection.
   </t>

   <t>
   The PDCP sublayer consists of functionalities for ciphering/deciphering,
   integrity protection/verification, re-ordering and in-order delivery,
   duplication and duplicate handling for higher layer packets, and acts as the
   anchor protocol to support handovers.
   </t>

   <t>
   The SDAP sublayer provides services to map QoS flows, as established by the
   5G core network, to data radio bearers (associated with logical channels),
   as used in the 5G RAN.
   </t>

   <t>
   Additionally, in RAN, the Radio Resource Control (RRC) protocol, handles the
   access control and configuration signalling for the aforementioned protocol
   layers. RRC messages are considered L3 and thus transmitted also via those
   radio protocol layers.
   </t>

   <t>
   To provide low latency and high reliability for one transmission link, i.e.,
   to transport data (or control signaling) of one radio bearer via one carrier,
   several features have been introduced on the user plane protocols for PHY
   and L2, as explained in the following.
   </t>

   </section><!-- Overview of Radio Protocol Stack   -->

   <section><name>Radio (PHY)</name>

   <t>
   NR is designed with native support of antenna arrays utilizing benefits from
   beamforming, transmissions over multiple MIMO layers and advanced receiver
   algorithms allowing effective interference cancellation. Those antenna
   techniques are the basis for high signal quality and effectiveness of
   spectral usage. Spatial diversity with up to 4 MIMO layers in UL and up to 8
   MIMO layers in DL is supported. Together with spatial-domain multiplexing,
   antenna arrays can focus power in desired direction to form beams. NR
   supports beam management mechanisms to find the best suitable beam for UE
   initially and when it is moving. In addition, gNBs can coordinate their
   respective DL and UL transmissions over the backhaul network keeping
   interference reasonably low, and even make transmissions or receptions from
   multiple points (multi-TRP). Multi-TRP can be used for repetition of data
   packet in time, in frequency or over multiple MIMO layers which can improve
   reliability even further.
   </t>

   <t>
   Any downlink transmission to a UE starts from resource allocation signaling
   over the Physical Downlink Control Channel (PDCCH). If it is successfully
   received, the UE will know about the scheduled transmission and may receive
   data over the Physical Downlink Shared Channel (PDSCH). If retransmission is
   required according to the HARQ scheme, a signaling of negative
   acknowledgement (NACK) on the Physical Uplink Control Channel (PUCCH) is
   involved and PDCCH together with PDSCH transmissions (possibly with
   additional redundancy bits) are transmitted and soft-combined with
   previously received bits. Otherwise, if no valid control signaling for
   scheduling data is received, nothing is transmitted on PUCCH (discontinuous
   transmission - DTX),and the base station upon detecting DTX will retransmit
   the initial data.
   </t>

   <t>
   An uplink transmission normally starts from a Scheduling Request (SR)  a
   signaling message from the UE to the base station sent via PUCCH.
   Once the scheduler is informed about buffer data in UE, e.g., by SR, the UE
   transmits a data packet on the Physical Uplink Shared Channel (PUSCH).
   Pre-scheduling not relying on SR is also possible (see following section).
   </t>

   <t>
   Since transmission of data packets require usage of control and data
   channels, there are several methods to maintain the needed reliability. NR
   uses Low Density Parity Check (LDPC) codes for data channels, Polar codes
   for PDCCH, as well as orthogonal sequences and Polar codes for PUCCH. For
   ultra-reliability of data channels, very robust (low spectral efficiency)
   Modulation and Coding Scheme (MCS) tables are introduced containing very low
   (down to 1/20) LDPC code rates using BPSK or QPSK. Also, PDCCH and PUCCH
   channels support multiple code rates including very low ones for the channel
   robustness.
   </t>

   <t>
   A connected UE reports downlink (DL) quality to gNB by sending Channel State
   Information (CSI) reports via PUCCH while uplink (UL) quality is measured
   directly at gNB. For both uplink and downlink, gNB selects the desired MCS
   number and signals it to the UE by Downlink Control Information (DCI) via
   PDCCH channel. For URLLC services, the UE can assist the gNB by advising
   that MCS targeting 10^-5 Block Error Rate (BLER) are used. Robust link
   adaptation algorithms can maintain the needed level of reliability
   considering a given latency bound.
   </t>

   <t>
   Low latency on the physical layer is provided by short transmission duration
   which is possible by using high Subcarrier Spacing (SCS) and the allocation
   of only one or a few Orthogonal Frequency Division Multiplexing (OFDM)
   symbols. For example, the shortest latency for the worst case in DL can be
   0.23ms and in UL can be 0.24ms according to (section 5.7.1 in
   <xref target='TR37910'/>). Moreover, if the initial transmission has failed,
   HARQ feedback can quickly be provided and an HARQ retransmission is
   scheduled.
   </t>

   <t>
   Dynamic multiplexing of data associated with different services is highly
   desirable for efficient use of system resources and to maximize system
   capacity. Assignment of resources for eMBB is usually done with regular
   (longer) transmission slots, which can lead to blocking of low latency
   services. To overcome the blocking, eMBB resources can be pre-empted and
   re-assigned to URLLC services. In this way, spectrally efficient assignments
   for eMBB can be ensured while providing flexibility required to ensure a
   bounded latency for URLLC services. In downlink, the gNB can notify the eMBB
   UE about pre-emption after it has happened, while in uplink there are two
   pre-emption mechanisms: special signaling to cancel eMBB transmission and
   URLLC dynamic power boost to suppress eMBB transmission.
   </t>

   </section><!-- Radio (PHY)   -->


  <section><name>Scheduling and QoS (MAC)</name>

   <t>
   One integral part of the 5G system is the Quality of Service (QoS) framework
   <xref target='TS23501'/>. QoS flows are setup by the 5G system for certain
   IP or Ethernet packet flows, so that packets of each flow receive the same
   forwarding treatment, i.e., in scheduling and admission control. QoS flows
   can for example be associated with different priority level, packet delay
   budgets and tolerable packet error rates. Since radio resources are
   centrally scheduled in NR, the admission control function can ensure that
   only those QoS flows are admitted for which QoS targets can be reached.
   </t>

   <t>
   NR transmissions in both UL and DL are scheduled by the gNB
   <xref target='TS38300'/>. This ensures radio resource efficiency, fairness
   in resource usage of the users and enables differentiated treatment of the
   data flows of the users according to the QoS targets of the flows. Those QoS
   flows are handled as data radio bearers or logical channels in NR RAN
   scheduling.
   </t>

   <t>
   The gNB can dynamically assign DL and UL radio resources to users,
   indicating the resources as DL assignments or UL grants via control channel
   to the UE. Radio resources are defined as blocks of OFDM symbols in spectral
   domain and time domain. Different lengths are supported in time domain,
   i.e., (multiple) slot or mini-slot lengths. Resources of multiple frequency
   carriers can be aggregated and jointly scheduled to the UE.
   </t>

   <t>
   Scheduling decisions are based, e.g., on channel quality measured on
   reference signals and reported by the UE (cf. periodical CSI reports for DL
   channel quality). The transmission reliability can be chosen in the
   scheduling algorithm, i.e., by link adaptation where an appropriate
   transmission format (e.g., robustness of modulation and coding scheme,
   controlled UL power) is selected for the radio channel condition of the UE.
   Retransmissions, based on HARQ feedback, are also controlled by the
   scheduler. The feedback transmission in HARQ loop introduces delays, but
   there are methods to minimize it by using short transmission formats,
   sub-slot feedback reporting and PUCCH carrier switching. If needed to
   avoid HARQ round-trip time delays, repeated transmissions can be also
   scheduled beforehand, to the cost of reduced spectral efficiency.
   </t>

   <t>
   In dynamic DL scheduling, transmission can be initiated immediately
   when DL data becomes available in the gNB. However, for dynamic UL
   scheduling, when data becomes available but no UL resources are available
   yet, the UE indicates the need for UL resources to the gNB via a (single bit)
   scheduling request message in the UL control channel. When thereupon UL
   resources are scheduled to the UE, the UE can transmit its data and may
   include a buffer status report, indicating the exact amount of data per
   logical channel still left to be sent. More UL resources may be scheduled
   accordingly. To avoid the latency introduced in the scheduling request loop,
   UL radio resources can also be pre-scheduled.
   </t>

   <t>
   In particular for periodical traffic patterns, the pre-scheduling can rely
   on the scheduling features DL Semi-Persistent Scheduling (SPS) and UL
   Configured Grant (CG). With these features, periodically recurring resources
   can be assigned in DL and UL. Multiple parallels of those configurations are
   supported, in order to serve multiple parallel traffic flows of the same UE.
   </t>

   <t>
   To support QoS enforcement in the case of mixed traffic with different QoS
   requirements, several features have recently been introduced. This way,
   e.g., different periodical critical QoS flows can be served together with
   best effort transmissions, by the same UE. Among others, these features
   (partly Release 16) are: 1) UL logical channel transmission restrictions
   allowing to map logical channels of certain QoS only to intended UL
   resources of a certain frequency carrier, slot-length, or CG configuration,
   and 2) intra-UE pre-emption and multiplexing, allowing critical UL
   transmissions to either pre-empt non-critical transmissions or being
   multiplexed with non-critical transmissions keeping different reliability
   targets.
   </t>

   <t>
   When multiple frequency carriers are aggregated, duplicate parallel
   transmissions can be employed (beside repeated transmissions on one
   carrier). This is possible in the Carrier Aggregation (CA) architecture
   where those carriers originate from the same gNB, or in the Dual
   Connectivity (DC) architecture where the carriers originate from different
   gNBs, i.e., the UE is connected to two gNBs in this case.  In both cases,
   transmission reliability is improved by this means of providing frequency
   diversity.
   </t>

   <t>
   In addition to licensed spectrum, a 5G system can also utilize unlicensed
   spectrum to offload non-critical traffic. This version of NR is called NR-U,
   part of 3GPP Release 16. The central scheduling approach applies also for
   unlicensed radio resources, but in addition also the mandatory channel
   access mechanisms for unlicensed spectrum, e.g., Listen Before Talk (LBT)
   are supported in NR-U. This way, by using NR, operators have and can control
   access to both licensed and unlicensed frequency resources.
   </t>

   </section><!-- Scheduling and QoS (MAC)   -->


  <section><name>Time-Sensitive Communications (TSC)</name>

   <t>
   Recent 3GPP releases have introduced various features to support multiple
   aspects of Time-Sensitive Communication (TSC), which includes Time-Sensitive
   Networking (TSN) and beyond as described in this section.
   </t>

   <t>
   The main objective of Time-Sensitive Networking (TSN) is to provide
   guaranteed data delivery within a guaranteed time window, i.e., bounded low
   latency. IEEE 802.1 TSN <xref target='IEEE802.1TSN'/> is a set of open
   standards that provide features to enable deterministic communication on
   standard IEEE 802.3 Ethernet <xref target='IEEE802.3'/>. TSN standards can
   be seen as a toolbox for traffic shaping, resource management, time
   synchronization, and reliability.
   </t>

   <t>
   A TSN stream is a data flow between one end station (Talker) to another end
   station (Listener). In the centralized configuration model, TSN bridges are
   configured by the Central Network Controller (CNC)
   <xref target='IEEE802.1Qcc'/> to provide deterministic connectivity for the
   TSN stream through the network. Time-based traffic shaping provided by
   Scheduled Traffic <xref target='IEEE802.1Qbv'/> may be used to achieve
   bounded low latency. The TSN tool for time synchronization is the
   generalized Precision Time Protocol (gPTP) <xref target='IEEE802.1AS'/>),
   which provides reliable time synchronization that can be used by end
   stations and by other TSN tools, e.g., Scheduled Traffic
   <xref target='IEEE802.1Qbv'/>. High availability, as a result of
   ultra-reliability, is provided for data flows by the Frame Replication and
   Elimination for Reliability (FRER) <xref target='IEEE802.1CB'/> mechanism.
   </t>

   <t>
   3GPP Release 16 includes integration of 5G with TSN, i.e., specifies
   functions for the 5G System (5GS) to deliver TSN streams such that the meet
   their QoS requirements. A key aspect of the integration is the 5GS appears
   from the rest of the network as a set of TSN bridges, in particular, one
   virtual bridge per User Plane Function (UPF) on the user plane. The 5GS
   includes TSN Translator (TT) functionality for the adaptation of the 5GS to
   the TSN bridged network and for hiding the 5GS internal procedures. The 5GS
   provides the following components:
   </t><ol type='%d.'>
      <li>interface to TSN controller, as per <xref target='IEEE802.1Qcc'/> for
      the fully centralized configuration model</li>
      <li>time synchronization via reception and transmission of gPTP PDUs
	  <xref target='IEEE802.1AS'/></li>
      <li>low latency, hence, can be integrated with Scheduled Traffic
	  <xref target='IEEE802.1Qbv'/></li>
      <li>reliability, hence, can be integrated with FRER
	  <xref target='IEEE802.1CB'/></li>
	  </ol><t>
   </t>

   <t>
   3GPP Release 17 <xref target='TS23501'/> introduced enhancements to
   generalize support for Time-Sensitive Communications (TSC) beyond TSN.
   This includes IP communications to provide time-sensitive service to, e.g.,
   Video, Imaging and Audio for Professional Applications (VIAPA). The system
   model of 5G acting as a TSN bridge in Release 16 has been reused to enable
   the 5GS acting as a TSC node in a more generic sense (which includes TSN
   bridge and IP node). In the case of TSC that does not involve TSN,
   requirements are given via exposure interface and the control plane provides
   the service based on QoS and time synchronization requests from an
   Application Function (AF).
   </t>

   <t>
   <xref target='fig-5g-tsn'/> shows an illustration of 5G-TSN integration
   where an industrial controller (Ind Ctrlr) is connected to industrial
   Input/Output devices (I/O dev) via 5G. The 5GS can directly transport
   Ethernet frames since Release 15, thus, end-to-end Ethernet connectivity is
   provided. The 5GS implements the required interfaces towards the TSN
   controller functions such as the CNC, thus adapts to the settings of the TSN
   network. A 5G user plane virtual bridge interconnects TSN bridges or connects
   end stations, e.g., I/O devices to the TSN network. TSN Translators (TTs),
   i.e., the Device-Side TSN Translator (DS-TT) at the UE and the Network-Side
   TSN Translator (NW-TT) at the UPF have a key role in the interconnection.
   Note that the introduction of 5G brings flexibility in various aspects, e.g.,
   more flexible network topology because a wireless hop can replace several
   wireline hops thus significantly reduce the number of hops end-to-end.
   <xref target='TSN5G'/> dives more into the integration of 5G with TSN.
   </t>

<figure anchor='fig-5g-tsn'><name>5G - TSN Integration</name>
<artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
                 +------------------------------+
                 | 5G System                    |
                 |                         +---+|
                 |     +-+ +-+ +-+ +-+ +-+ |TSN||
                 |     | | | | | | | | | | |AF |......+
                 |     +++ +++ +++ +++ +++ +-+-+|     .
                 |      |   |   |   |   |    |  |     .
                 |     -+---+---++--+-+-+--+-+- |     .
                 |          |    |    |    |    |  +--+--+
                 |         +++  +++  +++  +++   |  | TSN |
                 |         | |  | |  | |  | |   |  |Ctrlr+.......+
                 |         +++  +++  +++  +++   |  +--+--+       .
                 |                              |     .          .
                 |                              |     .          .
                 | +..........................+ |     .          .
                 | .      Virtual Bridge      . |     .          .
+---+            | . +--+--+   +---+ +---+--+ . |  +--+---+      .
|I/O+----------------+DS|UE+---+RAN+-+UPF|NW+------+ TSN  +----+ .
|dev|            | . |TT|  |   |   | |   |TT| . |  |bridge|    | .
+---+            | . +--+--+   +---+ +---+--+ . |  +------+    | .
                 | +..........................+ |     .      +-+-+-+
                 |                              |     .      | Ind |
                 | +..........................+ |     .      |Ctrlr|
                 | .      Virtual Bridge      . |     .      +-+---+
+---+  +------+  | . +--+--+   +---+ +---+--+ . |  +--+---+    |
|I/O+--+ TSN  +------+DS|UE+---+RAN+-+UPF|NW+------+ TSN  +----+
|dev|  |bridge|  | . |TT|  |   |   | |   |TT| . |  |bridge|
+---+  +------+  | . +--+--+   +---+ +---+--+ . |  +------+
                 | +..........................+ |
                 +------------------------------+

    <----------------- end-to-end Ethernet ------------------->
]]></artwork>
</figure>

   <t>
   NR supports accurate reference time synchronization in 1us accuracy level.
   Since NR is a scheduled system, an NR UE and a gNB are tightly synchronized
   to their OFDM symbol structures. A 5G internal reference time can be
   provided to the UE via broadcast or unicast signaling, associating a known
   OFDM symbol to this reference clock. The 5G internal reference time can be
   shared within the 5G network, i.e., radio and core network components.
   Release 16 has introduced interworking with gPTP for multiple time domains,
   where the 5GS acts as a virtual gPTP time-aware system and supports the
   forwarding of gPTP time synchronization information between end stations and
   bridges through the 5G user plane TTs. These account for the residence time
   of the 5GS in the time synchronization procedure. One special option is when
   the 5GS internal reference time is not only used within the 5GS, but also to
   the rest of the devices in the deployment, including connected TSN bridges
   and end stations. Release 17 includes further improvements, i.e., methods
   for propagation delay compensation in RAN, further improving the accuracy
   for time synchronization over-the-air, as well as the possibility for the
   TSN grandmaster clock to reside on the UE side. More extensions and
   flexibility were added to the time synchronization service making it general
   for TSC with additional support of other types of clocks and time
   distribution such as boundary clock, transparent clock peer-to-peer,
   transparent clock end-to-end, aside from the time-aware system used for TSN.
   Additionally, it is possible to use internal access stratum signaling to
   distribute timing (and not the usual (g)PTP messages), for which the required
   accuracy can be provided by the AF <xref target='TS23501'/>. The same time
   synchronization service is expected to be further extended and enhanced in
   Release 18 to support Timing Resiliency (according to study item
   <xref target='SP211634'/>), where the 5G system can provide a back-up or
   alternative timing source for the failure of the local GNSS source (or other
   primary timing source) used by the vertical.
   </t>

   <t>
   <!--
   IETF Deterministic Networking (DetNet) is the technology to support
   time-sensitive communications at the IP layer. 3GPP Release 18 includes a
   study <xref target='TR2370046'/> on whether and how to enable 3GPP support
   for DetNet such that a mapping is provided between DetNet and 5G. The support
   for DetNet is considered to be added via the TSC framework introduced for
   Release 17. The study includes what information needs to be exposed by the
   5G System and the translation of DetNet flow specification to 5G QoS
   parameters. Note that TSN is the primary subnetwork technology for DetNet.
   Thus, the DetNet over TSN work, e.g., <xref target='RFC9023'/>, can be
   leveraged via the TSN support built in 5G. As the standards are ready for
   such an approach, it is out of scope for the 3GPP Release 18 study item
   <xref target='TR2370046'/>.
   -->
   IETF Deterministic Networking (DetNet) is the technology to support
   time-sensitive communications at the IP layer. 3GPP Release 18 includes a
   study <xref target='TR2370046'/> on interworking between 5G and DetNet.
   Along the TSC framework introduced for Release 17, the 5GS acts as
   a DetNet node for the support of DetNet, see Figure 7.1-1 in
   <xref target='TR2370046'/>.
   The study provides details on how the 5GS is exposed by the Time Sensitive
   Communication and Time Synchronization Function (TSCTSF) to the DetNet
   controller as a router on a per UPF
   granularity (similarly to the per UPF Virtual TSN Bridge granularity
   shown in Figure 11). In particular, it is listed what parameters are
   provided by the TSCTSF to the DetNet controller. The study also
   includes how the TSCTSF maps DetNet flow parameters to 5G QoS
   parameters. Note that TSN is the primary subnetwork technology for DetNet.
   Thus, the DetNet over TSN work, e.g., <xref target='RFC9023'/>, can be
   leveraged via the TSN support built in 5G.

   </t>

   <t>
   Redundancy architectures were specified in order to provide reliability
   against any kind of failure on the radio link or nodes in the RAN and the
   core network. Redundant user plane paths can be provided based on the dual
   connectivity architecture, where the UE sets up two PDU sessions towards the
   same data network, and the 5G system makes the paths of the two PDU sessions
   independent as illustrated in <xref target='fig-5g-dual-ue'/>. There are two
   PDU sessions involved in the solution: the first spans from the UE via gNB1
   to UPF1, acting as the first PDU session anchor, while the second spans from
   the UE via gNB2 to UPF2, acting as second the PDU session anchor. The
   independent paths may continue beyond the 3GPP network. Redundancy Handling
   Functions (RHFs) are deployed outside of the 5GS, i.e., in Host A (the
   device) and in Host B (the network). RHF can implement replication and
   elimination functions as per <xref target='IEEE802.1CB'/> or the
   Packet Replication, Elimination, and Ordering Functions (PREOF) of IETF
   Deterministic Networking (DetNet) <xref target='RFC8655'/>.
   </t>

<figure anchor='fig-5g-single-ue'><name>Reliability with Single UE</name>
<artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
+........+
. Device . +------+      +------+      +------+
.        . + gNB1 +--N3--+ UPF1 |--N6--+      |
.        ./+------+      +------+      |      |
. +----+ /                             |      |
. |    |/.                             |      |
. | UE + .                             |  DN  |
. |    |\.                             |      |
. +----+ \                             |      |
.        .\+------+      +------+      |      |
+........+ + gNB2 +--N3--+ UPF2 |--N6--+      |
           +------+      +------+      +------+
]]></artwork>
</figure>

   <t>
   An alternative solution is that multiple UEs per device are used for user
   plane redundancy as illustrated in <xref target='fig-5g-dual-ue'/>. Each UE
   sets up a PDU session. The 5GS ensures that those PDU sessions of the
   different UEs are handled independently internal to the 5GS. There is no
   single point of failure in this solution, which also includes RHF outside
   of the 5G system, e.g., as per FRER or as PREOF specifications.
   </t>

<figure anchor='fig-5g-dual-ue'><name>Reliability with Dual UE</name>
<artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
+.........+
.  Device .
.         .
. +----+  .  +------+      +------+      +------+
. | UE +-----+ gNB1 +--N3--+ UPF1 |--N6--+      |
. +----+  .  +------+      +------+      |      |
.         .                              |  DN  |
. +----+  .  +------+      +------+      |      |
. | UE +-----+ gNB2 +--N3--+ UPF2 |--N6--+      |
. +----+  .  +------+      +------+      +------+
.         .
+.........+
]]></artwork>
</figure>

   <t>
   Note that the abstraction provided by the RHF and the location of the RHF
   being outside of the 5G system make 5G equally supporting integration for
   reliability both with FRER of TSN and PREOF of DetNet as they both rely on
   the same concept.
   </t>

   </section><!-- Time-Sensitive Networking (TSN) Integration)   -->


   </section><!-- Applicability to Deterministic Flows   -->


   <section><name>Summary</name>

   <t>
   5G technology enables deterministic communication. Based on the centralized
   admission control and the scheduling of the wireless resources, licensed or
   unlicensed, quality of service such as latency and reliability can be
   guaranteed. 5G contains several features to achieve ultra-reliable and low
   latency performance, e.g., support for different OFDM numerologies and
   slot-durations, as well as fast processing capabilities and redundancy
   techniques that lead to achievable latency numbers of below 1ms with
   99.999% or higher confidence.
   </t>

   <t>
   5G also includes features to support Industrial IoT use cases, e.g., via the
   integration of 5G with TSN. This includes 5G capabilities for each TSN
   component, latency, resource management, time synchronization, and
   reliability. Furthermore, 5G support for TSN can be leveraged when 5G is used
   as subnet technology for DetNet, in combination with or instead of TSN, which
   is the primary subnet for DetNet. In addition, the support for integration
   with TSN reliability was added to 5G by making DetNet reliability also
   applicable, due to the commonalities between TSN and DetNet reliability.
   Moreover, providing IP service is native to 5G and 3GPP Release 18 adds direct
   support for DetNet to 5G.
   </t>

   <t>
   Overall, 5G provides scheduled wireless segments with high reliability and
   availability. In addition, 5G includes capabilities for integration to IP
   networks.
   </t>

   </section><!-- Summary   -->

   </section> <!-- 5G -->


 <section><name>L-band Digital Aeronautical Communications System</name>
   <t>
One of the main pillars of the modern Air Traffic Management (ATM) system is the existence of a communication infrastructure that enables efficient aircraft guidance and safe separation in all phases of flight. Although current systems are technically mature, they are suffering from the VHF bands increasing saturation in high-density areas and the limitations posed by analogue radio. Therefore, aviation globally and the European Union (EU) in particular, strives for a sustainable modernization of the aeronautical communication infrastructure.
</t><t>
In the long-term, ATM communication shall transition from analogue VHF voice and VDL2 communication to more spectrum efficient digital data communication. The European ATM Master Plan foresees this transition to be realized for terrestrial communications by the development and implementation of the L-band Digital Aeronautical Communications System (LDACS).
LDACS shall enable IPv6 based air-ground communication related to the safety and regularity of the flight. The particular challenge is that no new frequencies can be made available for terrestrial aeronautical communication. It was thus necessary to develop procedures to enable the operation of LDACS in parallel with other services in the same frequency band.

</t>
   <section><name>Provenance and Documents</name>
       <t>
           The development of LDACS has already made substantial progress in the Single European Sky ATM Research (SESAR) framework, and is currently being continued in the follow-up program, SESAR2020 <xref target='RIH18'/>. A key objective of the SESAR activities is to develop, implement and validate a modern aeronautical data link able to evolve with aviation needs over long-term. To this end, an LDACS specification has been produced <xref target='GRA19'/> and is continuously updated; transmitter demonstrators were developed to test the spectrum compatibility of LDACS with legacy systems operating in the L-band <xref target='SAJ14'/>; and the overall system performance was analyzed by computer simulations, indicating that LDACS can fulfill the identified requirements <xref target='GRA11'/>.
       </t><t>
           LDACS standardization within the framework of the International Civil Aviation Organization (ICAO) started in December 2016. The ICAO standardization group has produced an initial Standards and Recommended Practices (SARPs) document <xref target='ICAO18'/>. The SARPs document defines the general characteristics of LDACS. The ICAO standardization group plans to produce an ICAO technical manual - the ICAO equivalent to a technical standard - within the next years. Generally, the group is open to input from all sources and develops LDACS in the open.
       </t><t>
           Up to now the LDACS standardization has been focused on the development of the physical layer and the data link layer, only recently have higher layers come into the focus of the LDACS development activities. There is currently no "IPv6 over LDACS" specification; however, SESAR2020 has started the testing of IPv6-based LDACS testbeds. The IPv6 architecture for the aeronautical telecommunication network is called the Future Communications Infrastructure (FCI). FCI shall support quality of service, diversity, and mobility under the umbrella of the "multi-link concept". This work is conducted by ICAO working group WG-I.
       </t><t>
           In addition to standardization activities several industrial LDACS prototypes have been built. One set of LDACS prototypes has been evaluated in flight trials confirming the theoretical results predicting the system performance <xref target='GRA18'/><xref target='SCH19'/>.
       </t>
   </section><!-- Provenance and Documents   -->

   <section><name>General Characteristics</name>
       <t>
           LDACS will become one of several wireless access networks connecting
           aircraft to the Aeronautical Telecommunications Network (ATN).  The
           LDACS access network contains several ground stations, each of them
           providing one LDACS radio cell.  The LDACS air interface is a
           cellular data link with a star-topology connecting aircraft to
           ground-stations with a full duplex radio link.  Each ground-station
           is the centralized instance controlling all air-ground communications
           within its radio cell.
       </t>
       <t>
           The user data rate of LDACS is 315 kbit/s to 1428 kbit/s on the forward link, and 294 kbit/s to 1390 kbit/s on the reverse link, depending on coding and modulation. Due to strong interference from legacy systems in the L-band, the most robust coding and modulation should be expected for initial deployment i.e. 315/294 kbit/s on the forward/reverse link, respectively.
       </t>
       <t>
           In addition to the communications capability, LDACS also offers a
           navigation capability. Ranging data, similar to DME (Distance
           Measuring Equipment), is extracted from the LDACS communication links
           between aircraft and LDACS ground stations. This results in LDACS
           providing an APNT (Alternative Position, Navigation and Timing)
           capability to supplement the existing on-board GNSS (Global Navigation
           Satellite System) without the need for additional bandwidth.
           Operationally, there will be no difference for pilots whether the
           navigation data are provided by LDACS or DME. This capability was
           flight tested and proven during the MICONAV flight trials in 2019
           <xref target="BAT19"/>.
       </t>
       <t>
           In previous works and during the MICONAV flight campaign in 2019, it
           was also shown, that LDACS can be used for surveillance capability.
           Filip et al. <xref target="FIL19"/>  shown passive radar capabilities of LDACS and
           Automatic Dependence Surveillance  Contract (ADS-C) was demonstrated
           via LDACS during the flight campaign 2019 <xref target="SCH19"/>.
       </t>

       <t>
           Since LDACS has been mainly designed for air traffic management communication it supports mutual entity authentication, integrity and confidentiality capabilities of user data messages and some control channel protection capabilities  <xref target="MAE18"/>, <xref target="MAE191"/>, <xref target="MAE192"/>, <xref target="MAE20"/>. <!--<xref target='MAE19'/>.-->
       </t>
       <t>
           Overall this makes LDACS the world's first truly integrated Communications, Navigation,done and Surveillance (CNS) system
           and is the worldwide most mature, secure, terrestrial long-range CNS
           technology for civil aviation.
       </t>


   </section><!-- General Characteristics  -->



   <section><name>Deployment and Spectrum</name>
       <t>
           LDACS has its origin in merging parts of the B-VHF <xref target="BRA06"/>, B-AMC
           <xref target="SCH08"/>, TIA-902 (P34) <xref target="HAI09"/>, and WiMAX IEEE 802.16e technologies
           <xref target="EHA11"/>. In 2007 the spectrum for LDACS was allocated at the World
           Radio Conference (WRC).
       </t>
       <t>
           It was decided to allocate the spectrum next to Distance Measuring
           Equipment (DME), resulting in an in-lay approach between the DME
           channels for LDAC <xref target="SCH14"/>.
       </t>
       <t>
           LDACS is currently being standardized by ICAO and several roll-out
           strategies are discussed:
       </t>
       <t>
           The LDACS data link provides enhanced capabilities to existing
           Aeronautical communications infrastructure enabling them to better
           support user needs and new applications. The deployment scalability of
           LDACS allows its implementation to start in areas where most needed to
           Improve immediately the performance of already fielded infrastructure.
           Later the deployment is extended based on operational demand.
           An attractive scenario for upgrading the existing VHF communication
           systems by adding an additional LDACS data link is described below.
       </t>
       <t>
           When considering the current VDL Mode 2 infrastructure and user base,
           a very attractive win-win situation comes about, when the
           technological advantages of LDACS are combined with the existing VDL
           mode 2 infrastructure. LDACS provides at least 50 time more capacity
           than VDL Mode 2 and is a natural enhancement to the existing VDL Mode
           2 business model. The advantage of this approach is that the VDL Mode
           2 infrastructure can be fully reused. Beyond that, it opens the way
           for further enhancements which can increase business efficiency and
           minimize investment risk. <xref target="ICAO19"/>

       </t>
    </section><!-- Deployment and Spectrum  -->

   <section><name>Applicability to Deterministic Flows</name>
       <t>
           As LDACS is a ground-based digital communications system for flight
           guidance and communications related to safety and regularity of
           flight, time-bounded deterministic arrival times for safety critical
           messages are a key feature for its successful deployment and roll-out.
       </t>

       <section><name>System Architecture</name>
           <t>
               Up to 512 Aircraft Station (AS) communicate to an LDACS Ground
               Station (GS) in the Reverse Link (RL). GS communicate to AS in
               the Forward Link (FL). Via an Access-Router (AC-R) GSs connect
               the LDACS sub-network to the global Aeronautical
               Telecommunications Network (ATN) to which the corresponding Air
               Traffic Services (ATS) and Aeronautical Operational Control (AOC)
               end systems are attached.
           </t>
       </section><!-- System Architecture  -->

       <section><name>Overview of The Radio Protocol Stack</name>
           <t>
               The protocol stack of LDACS is implemented in the AS and GS: It
               consists of the Physical Layer (PHY) with five major functional
               blocks above it.  Four are placed in the Data Link Layer (DLL) of the
               AS and GS: (1) Medium Access Layer (MAC), (2) Voice Interface (VI),
               (3) Data Link Service (DLS), and (4) LDACS Management Entity (LME).
               The last entity resides within the Sub-Network Layer: Sub-Network
               Protocol (SNP).  The LDACS network is externally connected to voice
               units, radio control units, and the ATN Network Layer.
           </t>
           <t>
           Communications between MAC and LME layer is split into four distinct control channels:
            The Broadcast Control Channel (BCCH) where LDACS ground stations announce their specific LDACS cell, including physical parameters and cell identification; the Random Access Channel (RACH) where LDACS airborne radios can request access to an LDACS cell; the Common Control Channel (CCCH) where LDACS ground stations allocate resources to aircraft radios, enabling the airborne side to transmit user payload; the Dedicated Control Channel (DCCH) where LDACS airborne radios can request user data resources from the LDACS ground station so the airborne side can transmit user payload.
            Communications between MAC and DLS layer is handled by the Data Channel (DCH) where user payload is handled.

           </t>
           <t>
               <xref target="fig_LDACSprotocolstack"/> shows the protocol stack of LDACS as implemented in the AS
               and GS.
           </t>
           <figure title="LDACS protocol stack in AS and GS"  anchor="fig_LDACSprotocolstack">
               <artwork>
                   <![CDATA[

         IPv6                   Network Layer
           |
           |
+------------------+  +----+
|        SNP       |--|    |   Sub-Network
|                  |  |    |   Layer
+------------------+  |    |
           |          | LME|
+------------------+  |    |
|        DLS       |  |    |   Logical Link
|                  |  |    |   Control Layer
+------------------+  +----+
           |             |
          DCH         DCCH/CCCH
           |          RACH/BCCH
           |             |
+--------------------------+
|           MAC            |   Medium Access
|                          |   Layer
+--------------------------+
           |
+--------------------------+
|           PHY            |   Physical Layer
+--------------------------+
           |
           |
         ((*))
         FL/RL              radio channels
                            separated by
                            Frequency Division Duplex

                   ]]>
               </artwork>
           </figure>
       </section><!-- Overview of The Radio Protocol Stack  -->

       <section><name>Radio (PHY)</name>
           <t>
               The physical layer provides the means to transfer data over the radio
               channel.  The LDACS ground-station supports bi-directional links to
               multiple aircraft under its control.  The forward link direction (FL;
               ground-to-air) and the reverse link direction (RL; air-to-ground) are
               separated by frequency division duplex.  Forward link and reverse
               link use a 500 kHz channel each.  The ground-station transmits a
               continuous stream of OFDM symbols on the forward link.  In the
               reverse link different aircraft are separated in time and frequency
               using a combination of Orthogonal Frequency-Division Multiple-Access
               (OFDMA) and Time-Division Multiple-Access (TDMA).  Aircraft thus
               transmit discontinuously on the reverse link with radio bursts sent
               in precisely defined transmission opportunities allocated by the
               ground-station.  The most important service on the PHY layer of LDACS
               is the PHY time framing service, which indicates that the PHY layer is
               ready to transmit in a given slot and to indicate PHY layer framing
               and timing to the MAC time framing service. LDACS does not support
               beam-forming or Multiple Input Multiple Output (MIMO).
           </t>
       </section><!-- Radio (PHY)  -->

       <section><name>Scheduling, Frame Structure and QoS (MAC)</name>
           <t>
               The data-link layer provides the necessary protocols to facilitate
               concurrent and reliable data transfer for multiple users.  The LDACS
               data link layer is organized in two sub-layers: The medium access
               sub-layer and the logical link control sub-layer.  The medium access
               sub-layer manages the organization of transmission opportunities in
               slots of time and frequency.  The logical link control sub-layer
               provides acknowledged point-to-point logical channels between the
               aircraft and the ground-station using an automatic repeat request
               protocol.  LDACS supports also unacknowledged point-to-point channels
               and ground-to-air broadcast.
               Before going more into depth about the LDACS medium access, the frame structure of LDACS is introduced:
           </t>
           <t>
               The LDACS framing structure for FL and RL is based on Super-Frames
               (SF) of 240 ms duration.  Each SF corresponds to 2000 OFDM symbols.
               The FL and RL SF boundaries are aligned in time (from the view of the
               GS).
           </t>
           <t>
               In the FL, an SF contains a Broadcast Frame of duration 6.72 ms (56
               OFDM symbols) for the Broadcast Control Channel (BCCH), and four
               Multi-Frames (MF), each of duration 58.32 ms (486 OFDM symbols).
           </t>
           <t>
               In the RL, each SF starts with a Random Access (RA) slot of length
               6.72 ms with two opportunities for sending RL random access frames
               for the Random Access Channel (RACH), followed by four MFs.  These
               MFs have the same fixed duration of 58.32 ms as in the FL, but a
               different internal structure
           </t>
           <t>
               <xref target="fig_LDACSframesuper"/> and <xref target="fig_LDACSframesmulti"/> illustrate the LDACS frame structure.
           </t>

           <figure title="SF structure for LDACS"  anchor="fig_LDACSframesuper">
               <artwork>
                   <![CDATA[

^
|     +------+------------+------------+------------+------------+
|  FL | BCCH |     MF     |     MF     |     MF     |     MF     |
F     +------+------------+------------+------------+------------+
r     <---------------- Super-Frame (SF) - 240ms ---------------->
e
q     +------+------------+------------+------------+------------+
u  RL | RACH |     MF     |     MF     |     MF     |     MF     |
e     +------+------------+------------+------------+------------+
n     <---------------- Super-Frame (SF) - 240ms ---------------->
c
y
|
----------------------------- Time ------------------------------>
|
                   ]]>
               </artwork>
           </figure>

           <figure title="MF structure for LDACS"  anchor="fig_LDACSframesmulti">
               <artwork>
                   <![CDATA[
^
|     +-------------+------+-------------+
|  FL |     DCH     | CCCH |     DCH     |
F     +-------------+------+-------------+
r     <---- Multi-Frame (MF) - 58.32ms -->
e
q     +------+---------------------------+
u  RL | DCCH |             DCH           |
e     +------+---------------------------+
n     <---- Multi-Frame (MF) - 58.32ms -->
c
y
|
-------------------- Time ------------------>
|
                   ]]>
               </artwork>
           </figure>

           <t>
           This fixed frame structure allows for a reliable and dependable
           transmission of data. Next, the LDACS medium
           access layer is introduced:
           </t>
           <t>
           LDACS medium access is always under the control of the ground-station
           of a radio cell.  Any medium access for the transmission of user data
           has to be requested with a resource request message stating the
           requested amount of resources and class of service.  The ground-
           station performs resource scheduling on the basis of these requests
           and grants resources with resource allocation messages.  Resource
           request and allocation messages are exchanged over dedicated
           contention-free control channels.
           </t>
           <t>
           LDACS has two mechanisms to request resources from the scheduler in
           the ground-station.

           Resources can either be requested "on demand", or permanently allocated by a LDACS ground station, with a given class of service.
            On the forward link, this is done
           locally in the ground-station, on the reverse link a dedicated
           contention-free control channel is used (Dedicated Control Channel
           (DCCH); roughly 83 bit every 60 ms).  A resource allocation is always
           announced in the control channel of the forward link (Common Control
           Channel (CCCH); variable sized).  Due to the spacing of the reverse
           link control channels of every 60 ms, a medium access delay in the
           same order of magnitude is to be expected.
           </t>
           <t>
           Resources can also be requested "permanently".  The permanent
           resource request mechanism supports requesting recurring resources in
           given time intervals.  A permanent resource request has to be
           canceled by the user (or by the ground-station, which is always in
           control).  User data transmissions over LDACS are therefore always
           scheduled by the ground-station, while control data uses statically
           (i.e. at net entry) allocated recurring resources (DCCH and CCCH).
           The current specification documents specify no scheduling algorithm.
           However performance evaluations so far have used strict priority
           scheduling and round robin for equal priorities for simplicity.  In
           the current prototype implementations LDACS classes of service are
           thus realized as priorities of medium access and not as flows.  Note
           that this can starve out low priority flows.  However, this is not
           seen as a big problem since safety related message always go first in
           any case.  Scheduling of reverse link resources is done in physical
           Protocol Data Units (PDU) of 112 bit (or larger if more aggressive
           coding and modulation is used).  Scheduling on the forward link is
           done Byte-wise since the forward link is transmitted continuously by
           the ground-station.
           </t>
           <t>
           In order to support diversity, LDACS supports handovers to other
           ground-stations on different channels.  Handovers may be initiated by
           the aircraft (break-before-make) or by the ground-station (make-
           before-break).  Beyond this, FCI diversity shall
           be implemented by the multi-link concept.
           </t>
       </section><!-- Scheduling, Frame Structure and QoS (MAC)  -->

   </section><!-- Applicability to deterministic flows  -->

   <section><name>Summary</name>
       <t>
           LDACS has been designed with applications related to the safety and
           regularity of the flight in mind.  It has therefore been designed as
           a deterministic wireless data link (as far as possible).
       </t>
       <t>
           It is a secure, scalable and spectrum efficient data link with
           embedded navigation capability and thus, is the first truly integrated
           CNS system recognized by ICAO. During flight tests the LDACS
           capabilities have been successfully demonstrated. A viable roll-out
           scenario has been developed which allows gradual introduction of LDACS
           with immediate use and revenues. Finally, ICAO is developing LDACS
           standards to pave the way for a successful roll-out in the near
           future.
       </t>
   </section><!-- Summary  -->

   </section><!-- title="L-band Digital Aeronautical Communications System" -->






   <section><name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>
    This specification does not require IANA action.
      </t>
   </section>

   <section anchor='sec'><name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>
    	Most RAW technologies integrate some authentication or encryption
    	mechanisms that were defined outside the IETF.
      </t>
   </section>


	<section><name>Contributors</name>
   <t> This document aggregates articles from authors specialized in each
   technologies. Beyond the main authors listed in the front page, the following
   contributors proposed additional text and refinement that improved the
   documertn greatly!
   			</t><dl  spacing='normal'>
   				<dt>Georgios Z. Papadopoulos:</dt><dd> Contributed to the TSCH section. </dd>
   				<dt>Nils Maeurer:</dt><dd> Contributed to the LDACS section. </dd>
   				<dt>Thomas Graeupl:</dt><dd> Contributed to the LDACS section. </dd>
				<dt>Torsten Dudda, Alexey Shapin, and Sara Sandberg:</dt><dd> Contributed to the 5G section. </dd>
                <dt>Rocco Di Taranto:</dt><dd> Contributed to the Wi-Fi section</dd>
                <dt>Rute Sofia:</dt><dd> Contributed to the Introduction and Terminology sections</dd>
   			</dl><t>

   		</t>
	</section>


	<section><name>Acknowledgments</name>
    <t>
    		Many thanks to the participants of the RAW WG where a lot of the work discussed here happened, and Malcolm Smith for his review of the 802.11 section. Special thanks for post directirate and IESG reviewers, Victoria Pritchard and Carlos Jesus Bernardos Cano.
    </t>
	</section><!-- ack -->
</middle>


<back>
<displayreference   target="IEEE802154"            to="IEEE Std 802.15.4"/>
<displayreference   target="IEEE80211"             to="IEEE Std 802.11"/>
<displayreference   target="IEEE8021Qat"           to="IEEE Std 802.1Qat"/>
<displayreference   target="IEEE80211ad"           to="IEEE Std 802.11ad"/>
<displayreference   target="IEEE80211ax"           to="IEEE Std 802.11ax"/>
<displayreference   target="IEEE80211ay"           to="IEEE Std 802.11ay"/>
<displayreference   target="IEEE80211be"           to="IEEE 802.11be WIP"/>


   <references><name>Normative References</name>
   <xi:include href='http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5673.xml'/> <!-- Industrial Routing Requirements in Low-Power and Lossy Networks -->
   <xi:include href='http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8200.xml'/> <!-- Internet Protocol, Version 6 (IPv6) Specification -->
   <xi:include href='http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8557.xml'/>
   <!-- DetNet PS -->
   <xi:include href='http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8655.xml'/>
   <!-- detnet-architecture -->
   <xi:include href='http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9030.xml'/> <!-- 6Tisch Archi -->
   </references>
   <references><name>Informative References</name>
      <xi:include href='http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8480.xml'/> <!-- 6P Protocol Specification -->


     <!--  <xi:include href='http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8938.xml'/> detnet-dataplane -->

      <xi:include href='http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9033.xml'/> <!-- 6Tisch MSF -->


      <xi:include href='http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6550.xml'/> <!-- RPL -->
      <xi:include href='http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6551.xml'/> <!-- RPL metrics -->
      <xi:include href='http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6291.xml'/> <!-- OAM guidelines -->
      <xi:include href='http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7276.xml'/> <!-- OAM -->
      <xi:include href='http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8279.xml'/> <!-- Mcast BIER -->
	  <xi:include href='http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9023.xml'/> <!-- DetNet IP over TSN -->
      <xi:include href='http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9262.xml'/> <!-- bier-te-architecture -->
      <xi:include href='http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-raw-architecture.xml'/>
      <xi:include href='http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-roll-nsa-extension.xml'/>
      <xi:include href='http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.papadopoulos-paw-pre-reqs.xml'/>
      <xi:include href='http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.thubert-bier-replication-elimination.xml'/>
      <xi:include href='http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.thubert-6lo-bier-dispatch.xml'/>
      <xi:include href='http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-6tisch-coap.xml'/>

      <reference anchor='IEEE802154'>
         <front>
            <title>IEEE Std 802.15.4, Part. 15.4: Wireless Medium Access
            Control (MAC) and Physical Layer (PHY) Specifications for Low-Rate
            Wireless Personal Area Networks
            </title>
            <author>
               <organization>IEEE standard for Information Technology</organization>
            </author>
            <date/>
         </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='IEEE80211'
                 target="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/9363693" >
        <front>
          <title>
            IEEE Standard 802.11 - IEEE Standard for Information
            Technology - Telecommunications and information exchange
            between systems Local and metropolitan area networks -
            Specific requirements - Part 11: Wireless LAN Medium
            Access Control (MAC) and Physical Layer (PHY)
            Specifications.
          </title>
          <author>
               <organization>IEEE standard for Information Technology</organization>
           </author>
          <date/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='IEEE80211ax'
                 target="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/9442429">
        <front>
          <title>
            802.11ax: Enhancements for High Efficiency WLAN
          </title>
          <author>
               <organization>IEEE standard for Information Technology</organization>
           </author>
          <date year='2021'/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='IEEE80211ay'
                 target="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/9502046/">
        <front>
          <title>
            802.11ay: Enhanced throughput for operation in license-exempt bands above 45 GHz
          </title>
          <author>
               <organization>IEEE standard for Information Technology</organization>
           </author>
          <date year='2021'/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='IEEE80211ad'
                 target="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/6392842/">
        <front>
          <title>
            802.11ad: Enhancements for very high throughput in the 60 GHz band
          </title>
          <author></author>
          <date year='2012'/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='IEEE80211be'
                 target="https://mentor.ieee.org/802.11/dcn/18/11-18-1231-04-0eht-eht-draft-proposed-par.docx">
        <front>
          <title>
            802.11be: Extreme High Throughput PAR
          </title>
          <author>
               <organization>IEEE standard for Information Technology</organization>
           </author>
          <date/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='IEEE8021Qat'>
        <front>
          <title>
            802.1Qat: Stream Reservation Protocol
          </title>
          <author></author>
          <date/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='Cavalcanti_2019'>
        <front>
          <title>
            Extending Time Distribution and
       		Timeliness Capabilities over the Air to Enable Future Wireless Industrial
       		Automation Systems, the Proceedings of IEEE
          </title>
          <author initials='' surname='Dave Cavalcanti et al.' fullname='Dave Cavalcanti'>
               <organization>IEEE standard for Information Technology</organization>
           <address></address>
          </author>
          <date month='June' year='2019'/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='Nitsche_2015'>
        <front>
          <title>
            IEEE 802.11ad: directional 60 GHz communication for multi-Gigabit-per-second Wi-Fi
          </title>
          <author initials='' surname='Thomas Nitsche et al.' fullname='Thomas Nitsche'>
               <organization>IEEE standard for Information Technology</organization>
           <address></address>
          </author>
          <date month='December' year='2014'/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='Ghasempour_2017'>
        <front>
          <title>
            802.11ay: Next-Generation 60 GHz Communications for 100 Gb/s Wi-Fi
          </title>
          <author initials='' surname='Yasaman Ghasempour et al.' fullname='Yasaman Ghasempour'>
               <organization>IEEE standard for Information Technology</organization>
           <address></address>
          </author>
          <date month='December' year='2017'/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='IEEE_doc_11-18-2009-06'>
        <front>
          <title>
            802.11 Real-Time Applications (RTA) Topic Interest Group (TIG) Report
          </title>
          <author>
               <organization>IEEE standard for Information Technology</organization>
           </author>
          <date month='November' year='2018'/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='IEEE_doc_11-19-0373-00'>
        <front>
          <title>
            Time-Sensitive Applications Support in EHT
          </title>
          <author initials='' surname='Kevin Stanton et Al.' fullname='Kevin Stanton'>
               <organization>IEEE standard for Information Technology</organization>
           <address></address>
          </author>
          <date month='March' year='2019'/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='morell13'>
        <front>
          <title>
            Label switching over IEEE802.15.4e networks
          </title>
          <author initials='' surname='Antoni Morell et al.' fullname='Antoni Morell et al.'>
            <organization>Trans. Emerging Tel. Tech., 24: 458-475. doi:10.1002/ett.2650</organization><address></address>
          </author>
          <date month='April' year='2013'/>
        </front>
      </reference>

   <reference anchor='dearmas16'>
        <front>
          <title>
            Determinism through path diversity: Why packet replication makes sense
          </title>
          <author initials='' surname='Jesica de Armas et al.' fullname='Jesica de Armas et al.'>
            <organization>In 2016 International Conference on Intelligent Networking and Collaborative Systems (INCoS)</organization><address></address>
          </author>
          <date month='September' year='2016'/>
        </front>
      </reference>


      <reference anchor='vilajosana19'>
        <front>
          <title>
            6TiSCH: Industrial Performance for IPv6 Internet-of-Things Networks
          </title>
          <author initials='' surname='Xavier Vilajosana et al.' fullname='Xavier Vilajosana et al.'>
            <organization>Proceedings of the IEEE, vol. 107, no. 6, pp. 1153-1165 </organization><address></address>
          </author>
          <date month='June' year='2019'/>
        </front>
      </reference>
	  
	  <reference anchor='vilajosana21'>
        <front>
          <title>
            IETF 6TiSCH: A Tutorial
          </title>
          <author initials='' surname='Xavier Vilajosana et al.' fullname='Xavier Vilajosana et al.'>
            <organization>IEEE Communications Surveys and Tutorials, vol. 22, no. 1, pp. 595-615 </organization><address></address>
          </author>
          <date month='March' year='2021'/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='ISA100.11a' target='http://www.isa100wci.org/en-US/Documents/PDF/3405-ISA100-WirelessSystems-Future-broch-WEB-ETSI.aspx'>
        <front>
          <title>ISA100.11a, Wireless Systems for Automation, also IEC 62734</title>

          <author>
            <organization>ISA/IEC</organization>
          </author>

          <date year='2011'/>
        </front>
      </reference>


      <reference anchor='WirelessHART'>
         <front>
            <title>Industrial Communication Networks - Wireless Communication
            Network and Communication Profiles - WirelessHART - IEC 62591</title>
            <author>
               <organization>www.hartcomm.org</organization>
            </author>
            <date year='2010'/>
         </front>
      </reference>


      <reference anchor='PCE' target='https://dataTracker.ietf.org/doc/charter-ietf-pce/'>
         <front>
            <title>Path Computation Element</title>
            <author>
               <organization>IETF</organization>
            </author>
            <date/>
         </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='CCAMP' target='https://dataTracker.ietf.org/doc/charter-ietf-ccamp/'>
         <front>
            <title>Common Control and Measurement Plane</title>
            <author>
               <organization>IETF</organization>
            </author>
            <date/>
         </front>
      </reference>

      <!--reference anchor="MPLS" target="https://dataTracker.ietf.org/doc/charter-ietf-mpls/">
         <front>
            <title>Multiprotocol Label Switching</title>
            <author>
               <organization>IETF</organization>
            </author>
            <date/>
         </front>
      </reference-->

      <reference anchor='TiSCH' target='https://dataTracker.ietf.org/doc/charter-ietf-6tisch/'>
         <front>
            <title>IPv6 over the TSCH mode over 802.15.4</title>
            <author>
               <organization>IETF</organization>
            </author>
            <date/>
         </front>
      </reference>


      <reference anchor='RIH18'>
         <front>
            <title>L-band Digital Aeronautical Communications System (LDACS) Activities in SESAR2020</title>
            <author fullname='C. Rihacek'>
               <organization>German Aerospace Center (DLR)</organization></author>
            <author fullname='B. Haindl'></author>
            <author fullname='P. Fantappie'></author>
            <author fullname='S. Pierattelli'></author>
            <author fullname='Thomas Grupl'>
               <organization>German Aerospace Center (DLR)</organization>
               </author>
            <author fullname='M. Schnell'>
               <organization>German Aerospace Center (DLR)</organization></author>
            <author fullname='N. Fistas'></author>
            <date month='April' year='2018'/>
         </front>
         <seriesInfo name='Proceedings of the Integrated Communications Navigation and Surveillance Conference (ICNS)' value='Herndon, VA, USA'/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='GRA19'>
         <front>
            <title>LDACS A/G Specification</title>
            <author fullname='Thomas Grupl'>
               <organization>German Aerospace Center (DLR)</organization></author>
            <author fullname='C. Rihacek'>
               <organization>German Aerospace Center (DLR)</organization></author>
            <author fullname='B. Haindl'>
               <organization>German Aerospace Center (DLR)</organization></author>
            <date month='February' year='2019'/>
         </front>
         <seriesInfo name='SESAR2020' value='PJ14-02-01 D3.3.010'/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='SAJ14'>
         <front>
            <title>WA04 D22 Test Report for Assessing LDACS1 Transmitter Impact upon DME/TACAN Receivers</title>
            <author fullname='M. Sajatovic'></author>
            <author fullname='H. Gnzel'></author>
            <author fullname='S. Mller'></author>
            <date month='April' year='2014'/>
         </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='GRA11'>
         <front>
            <title>L-DACS1 Data Link Layer Evolution of ATN/IPS</title>
            <author fullname='Thomas Grupl'>
               <organization>German Aerospace Center (DLR)</organization>
               </author>
            <author fullname='M. Ehammer'></author>
            <date month='October' year='2011'/>
         </front>
        <seriesInfo name='Proceedings of the 30th IEEE/AIAA Digital Avionics Systems Conference (DASC)' value='Seattle, WA, USA'/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='ICAO18'>
         <front>
            <title>L-Band Digital Aeronautical Communication System (LDACS)</title>
            <author>
               <organization>International Civil Aviation Organization (ICAO)</organization>
               </author>
            <date month='July' year='2018'/>
         </front>
        <seriesInfo name='International Standards and Recommended Practices' value='Annex 10 - Aeronautical Telecommunications, Vol. III - Communication Systems'/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='GRA18'>
         <front>
            <title>L-band Digital Aeronautical Communications System (LDACS) flight trials in the national German project MICONAV</title>
            <author fullname='Thomas Grupl et al.'></author>
            <date month='April' year='2018'/>
         </front>
        <seriesInfo name='Proceedings of the Integrated Communications, Navigation, Surveillance Conference (ICNS)' value='Herndon, VA, USA'/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='SCH19' target='https://www.dlr.de/dlr/en/desktopdefault.aspx/tabid-10081/151_read-32951/#/gallery/33877'>
         <front>
            <title>DLR tests digital communications technologies combined with additional navigation functions for the first time</title>
            <author fullname='M. Schnell'>
               <organization>German Aerospace Center (DLR)</organization></author>
            <date day='03' month='March' year='2019'/>
         </front>
      </reference>


      <reference anchor='TR37910' target='https://portal.3gpp.org/desktopmodules/Specifications/SpecificationDetails.aspx?specificationId=3190'>
        <front>
          <title>Study on self evaluation towards IMT-2020 submission</title>
          <seriesInfo name="3GPP" value="TR 37.910"/>
          <author>
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true">3GPP</organization>
          </author>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='TR38824' target='https://portal.3gpp.org/desktopmodules/Specifications/SpecificationDetails.aspx?specificationId=3498'>
        <front>
          <title>Study on physical layer enhancements for NR ultra-reliable and low latency case (URLLC)</title>
          <seriesInfo name="3GPP" value="TR 38.824"/>
          <author>
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true">3GPP</organization>
          </author>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='TR38825' target='https://portal.3gpp.org/desktopmodules/Specifications/SpecificationDetails.aspx?specificationId=3492'>
        <front>
          <title>Study on NR industrial Internet of Things (IoT)</title>
          <seriesInfo name="3GPP" value="TR 38.825"/>
          <author>
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true">3GPP</organization>
          </author>
        </front>
      </reference>

	  <reference anchor='TS22104' target='https://portal.3gpp.org/desktopmodules/Specifications/SpecificationDetails.aspx?specificationId=3528'>
        <front>
          <title>Service requirements for cyber-physical control applications in vertical domains</title>
          <seriesInfo name="3GPP" value="TS 22.104"/>
          <author>
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true">3GPP</organization>
          </author>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='TR22804' target='https://portal.3gpp.org/desktopmodules/Specifications/SpecificationDetails.aspx?specificationId=3187'>
        <front>
          <title>Study on Communication for Automation in Vertical domains (CAV)</title>
          <seriesInfo name="3GPP" value="TS 22.804"/>
          <author>
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true">3GPP</organization>
          </author>
        </front>
      </reference>

	  <reference anchor='TS23501' target='https://portal.3gpp.org/desktopmodules/Specifications/SpecificationDetails.aspx?specificationId=3144'>
        <front>
          <title>System architecture for the 5G System (5GS)</title>
          <seriesInfo name="3GPP" value="TS 23.501"/>
          <author>
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true">3GPP</organization>
          </author>
        </front>
      </reference>

       <reference anchor='TS38300' target='https://portal.3gpp.org/desktopmodules/Specifications/SpecificationDetails.aspx?specificationId=3191'>
        <front>
          <title>NR Overall description</title>
          <seriesInfo name="3GPP" value="TS 38.300"/>
          <author>
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true">3GPP</organization>
          </author>
        </front>
      </reference>

	  <reference anchor='RP210854' target='https://www.3gpp.org/ftp/tsg_ran/TSG_RAN/TSGR_91e/Docs/RP-210854.zip'>
        <front>
          <title>Revised WID: Enhanced Industrial Internet of Things (IoT) and ultra-reliable and low latency communication (URLLC) support for NR</title>
          <seriesInfo name="3GPP" value="RP-210854"/>
          <author>
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true">3GPP</organization>
          </author>
		  <date month='March' year='2021'/>
        </front>
      </reference>



	  <reference anchor='TR2370046' target='https://portal.3gpp.org/desktopmodules/Specifications/SpecificationDetails.aspx?specificationId=3994'>
        <front>
          <title>Study on 5GS DetNet interworking</title>
          <seriesInfo name="3GPP" value="TR23.700-46"/>
          <author>
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true">3GPP</organization>
          </author>
		  <date month='August' year='2022'/>
        </front>
      </reference>


	  <!--reference anchor='SP211633' target='https://www.3gpp.org/ftp/tsg_sa/TSG_SA/TSGS_94E_Electronic_2021_12/Docs/SP-211633.zip'>
        <front>
          <title>New SID: Extensions to the TSC Framework to support DetNet</title>
          <seriesInfo name="3GPP" value="SP-211633"/>
          <author>
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true">3GPP</organization>
          </author>
		  <date month='December' year='2021'/>
        </front>
      </reference-->

	  <reference anchor='SP211634' target='https://www.3gpp.org/ftp/tsg_sa/TSG_SA/TSGS_94E_Electronic_2021_12/Docs/SP-211634.zip '>
        <front>
          <title>Study on 5G Timing Resiliency, TSC, and URLLC enhancements</title>
          <seriesInfo name="3GPP" value="SP-211634"/>
          <author>
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true">3GPP</organization>
          </author>
		  <date month='December' year='2021'/>
        </front>
      </reference>

	  <reference anchor='IMT2020' target='https://www.itu.int/en/ITU-R/study-groups/rsg5/rwp5d/imt-2020/Pages/default.aspx'>
        <front>
          <title>ITU towards IMT for 2020 and beyond</title>
          <author></author>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="IEEE802.1TSN" target="http://www.ieee802.org/1/pages/tsn.html" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="IEEE802.1TSN">
        <front>
          <title>Time-Sensitive Networking (TSN) Task Group</title>
          <author>
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true">IEEE 802.1</organization>
          </author>
        </front>
      </reference>

     <reference anchor="IEEE802.1AS" target="https://standards.ieee.org/content/ieee-standards/en/standard/802_1AS-2020.html" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="IEEE802.1AS">
        <front>
          <title>IEEE Standard for Local and metropolitan area networks -- Timing and Synchronization for Time-Sensitive Applications</title>
          <seriesInfo name="IEEE" value="802.1AS-2020"/>
          <author>
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true">IEEE</organization>
          </author>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="IEEE802.1CB" target="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/8091139" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="IEEE802.1CB">
        <front>
          <title>IEEE Standard for Local and metropolitan area networks -- Frame Replication and Elimination for Reliability</title>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1109/IEEEStd2017.8091139"/>
          <seriesInfo name="IEEE" value="802.1CB-2017"/>
          <author>
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true">IEEE</organization>
          </author>
          <date/>
        </front>
     </reference>

     <reference anchor="IEEE802.1Qbv" target="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/7440741" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="IEEE802.1Qbv">
        <front>
          <title>IEEE Standard for Local and metropolitan area networks -- Bridges and Bridged Networks -- Amendment 25: Enhancements for Scheduled Traffic</title>
          <seriesInfo name="IEEE" value="802.1Qbv-2015"/>
          <author>
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true">IEEE</organization>
          </author>
        </front>
      </reference>

	  <reference anchor="IEEE802.1Qcc" target="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/8514112" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="IEEE802.1Qcc">
        <front>
          <title>IEEE Standard for Local and metropolitan area networks -- Bridges and Bridged Networks -- Amendment 31: Stream Reservation Protocol (SRP) Enhancements and Performance Improvements</title>
          <seriesInfo name="IEEE" value="802.1Qcc-2018"/>
          <author>
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true">IEEE</organization>
          </author>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="IEEE802.3" target="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/8457469" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="IEEE802.3">
        <front>
          <title>IEEE Standard for Ethernet</title>
          <seriesInfo name="IEEE" value="802.3-2018"/>
          <author>
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true">IEEE</organization>
          </author>
        </front>
      </reference>

     <reference anchor="TSN5G" target="https://5g-acia.org/whitepapers/integration-of-5g-with-time-sensitive-networking-for-industrial-communications" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="TSN5G">
        <front>
          <title>Integration of 5G with Time-Sensitive Networking for Industrial Communications</title>
          <seriesInfo name="5G-ACIA" value="whitepaper"/>
          <author>
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true">5G-ACIA</organization>
          </author>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="MAE18"> <!--REF9-->
      <front>
      <title>A Cybersecurity Architecture for the L-band Digital Aeronautical Communications System (LDACS)
      </title>
      <author initials="N." surname="Maeurer"/>
      <author initials="A." surname="Bilzhause"/>
      <date year="2017"/>
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name='IEEE 37th Digital Avionics Systems Conference (DASC), pp. 1-10, London, UK' value=''/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="MAE191"> <!--REF2-->
      <front>
      <title>Towards Successful Realization of the LDACS Cybersecurity Architecture: An Updated Datalink Security Threat- and Risk Analysis
      </title>
      <author initials="N." surname="Maeurer"/>
      <author initials="C." surname="Schmitt"/>
      <date year="2019"/>
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name='IEEE Integrated Communications, Navigation and Surveillance Conference (ICNS),  pp. 1-13, Herndon, VA, USA' value=''/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="ICAO19"> <!--REF2-->
      <front>
      <title>TLDACS White PaperA Roll-out Scenario
      </title>
      <author>
      <organization showOnFrontPage="true">International Civil Aviation Organization (ICAO)</organization>
      </author>
      <date year="2019" month="October"/>
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name='Working Paper
      COMMUNICATIONS PANELDATA COMMUNICATIONS INFRASTRUCTURE
      WORKING GROUP, Montreal, Canada
      ' value=''/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="MAE192"> <!--REF1-->
      <front>
      <title>Evaluation of the LDACS Cybersecurity Implementation
      </title>
      <author initials="N." surname="Maeurer"/>
      <author initials="T." surname="Graeupl"/>
      <author initials="C." surname="Schmitt"/>
      <date year="2019" month="September"/>
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name='IEEE 38th Digital Avionics Systems Conference (DACS), pp. 1-10, San Diego, CA, USA' value=''/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="MAE20"> <!--REF1-->
      <front>
      <title>Comparing Different Diffie-Hellman Key Exchange Flavors for LDACS
      </title>
      <author initials="N." surname="Maeurer"/>
      <author initials="T." surname="Graeupl"/>
      <author initials="C." surname="Schmitt"/>
      <date year="2019" month="October"/>
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name='IEEE 39th Digital Avionics Systems Conference (DACS), pp. 1-10, San Diego, CA, USA' value=''/>
      </reference>


      <reference anchor="FIL19"> <!--REF1-->
      <front>
      <title>LDACS-
      Based Non-Cooperative Surveillance Multistatic Radar Design
      and Detection Coverage Assessment
      </title>
      <author initials="A." surname="Filip-Dhaubhadel"/>
      <author initials="D." surname="Shutin"/>
      <date year="2019" month="September"/>
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name='IEEE 38th Digital Avionics Systems Conference (DACS), pp. 1-10, San Diego, CA, USA' value=''/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="BAT19"> <!--REF2-->
      <front>
      <title>Real-Time Demonstration of
      Integrated Communication and Navigation Services Using
      LDACS
      </title>
      <author initials="G." surname="Battista"/>
      <author initials="O." surname="Osechas"/>
      <author initials="S." surname="Narayanan"/>
      <author initials="O.G." surname="Crespillo"/>
      <author initials="D." surname="Gerbeth"/>
      <author initials="N." surname="Maeurer"/>
      <author initials="D." surname="Mielke"/>
      <author initials="T." surname="Graeupl"/>
      <date year="2019"/>
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name='IEEE Integrated Communications, Navigation and Surveillance Conference (ICNS),  pp. 1-12, Herndon, VA, USA' value=''/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="BRA06"> <!--REF1-->
      <front>
      <title>B-VHF -Selected Simulation Results and Final Assessment
      </title>
      <author initials="S." surname="Brandes"/>
      <author initials="M." surname="Schnell"/>
      <author initials="C.H." surname="Rokitansky"/>
      <author initials="M." surname="Ehammer"/>
      <author initials="T." surname="Graeupl"/>
      <author initials="H." surname="Steendam"/>
      <author initials="M." surname="Guenach"/>
      <author initials="C." surname="Rihacek"/>
      <author initials="B." surname="Haindl"/>
      <date year="2019" month="September"/>
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name='IEEE 25th Digital Avionics Systems Conference (DACS), pp. 1-12, New York, NY, USA' value=''/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="SCH08"> <!--REF2-->
      <front>
      <title>B-AMC -
      Broadband Aeronautical Multi-carrier Communications
      </title>
      <author initials="M." surname="Schnell"/>
      <author initials="S." surname="Brandes"/>
      <author initials="S." surname="Gligorevic"/>
      <author initials="C.H." surname="Rokitansky"/>
      <author initials="M." surname="Ehammer"/>
      <author initials="T." surname="Graeupl"/>
      <author initials="C." surname="Rihacek"/>
      <author initials="M." surname="Sajatovic"/>
      <date year="2008" month="April"/>
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name='IEEE 8th Integrated Communications, Navigation and Surveillance Conference (ICNS),  pp. 1-13, New York, NY, USA' value=''/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="HAI09"> <!--REF2-->
      <front>
      <title>Improvement of L-DACS1 Design by Combining B-AMC with P34
      and WiMAX Technologies
      </title>
      <author initials="B." surname="Haindl"/>
      <author initials="C." surname="Rihacek"/>
      <author initials="M." surname="Sajatovic"/>
      <author initials="B." surname="Phillips"/>
      <author initials="J." surname="Budinger"/>
      <author initials="M." surname="Schnell"/>
      <author initials="D." surname="Kamiano"/>
      <author initials="W." surname="Wilson"/>
      <date year="2009" month="May"/>
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name='IEEE 9th Integrated Communications, Navigation and Surveillance Conference (ICNS),  pp. 1-8, New York, NY, USA' value=''/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="EHA11"> <!--REF1-->
      <front>
      <title>AeroMACS - An Airport
      Communications System
      </title>
      <author initials="M." surname="Ehammer"/>
      <author initials="T." surname="Graeupl"/>
      <date year="2011" month="September"/>
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name='IEEE 30th Digital Avionics Systems Conference (DACS), pp. 1-16, New York, NY, USA' value=''/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="SCH14"> <!--BELL19-->
      <front>
      <title>LDACS: Future Aeronautical Communications for Air-
      Traffic Management

      </title>
      <author initials="M." surname="Schnell"/>
      <author initials="U." surname="Epple"/>
      <author initials="D." surname="Shutin"/>
      <author initials="N." surname="Schneckenburger"/>
      <date year="2017"  />
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name='IEEE Communications Magazine, 52(5),
      104-110
      ' value=''/>
      </reference>


      <reference anchor="Cavalcanti1287" target='https://mentor.ieee.org/802.11/dcn/19/11-19-1287'> <!--Cavalcanti1287-->
      <front>
      <title>TSN support in 802.11 and potential extensions for TGbe

      </title>
      <author initials="D." surname="Cavalcanti"/>
      <author initials="G." surname="Venkatesan"/>
      <author initials="L." surname="Cariou"/>
      <author initials="C." surname="Cordeiro"/>
      <date year="2019"  />
      </front>
      </reference>


      <reference anchor="Sudhakaran2021" target='https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/abstract/document/9483447'> <!--SURUTH -->
      <front>
      <title>
         Wireless Time Sensitive Networking for Industrial Collaborative Robotic Workcells
      </title>
      <author initials="S." surname="Sudhakaran"/>
      <author initials="K." surname="Montgomery"/>
      <author initials="M." surname="Kashef"/>
      <author initials="D." surname="Cavalcanti"/>
      <author initials="R." surname="Candell"/>
      <date year="2021"  />
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name='17th IEEE International Conference on Factory Communication Systems (WFCS)' value=''/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Fang_2021" > <!--FANG -->
      <front>
      <title>
         Wireless TSN with Multi-Radio Wi-Fi
      </title>
      <author initials="J." surname="Fang"/>
      <author initials="D." surname="Cavalcanti"/>
      <author initials="C." surname="Cordeiro"/>
      <author initials="C." surname="Cheng"/>
      <date year="2021"  />
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name='IEEE International Conference on Standards for Communications and Networking, December 2021.' value=''/>
      </reference>

   </references>
</back>

</rfc>

<!-- CONVERT WARNING: wide character found at character 2041 of the output -->
